Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: Senate President, the Presiding Officer, and Senator-Judges of the Impeachment Court.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The Sergeant at Arms is directed to make the proclamation.
Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: All persons are commanded to keep silent under the pain of penalty while the Impeachment Court is in session for the trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The impeachment trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte is hereby called to order. We shall be led in prayer by Senator-Judge Robin Hood Padilla.
Sen. Robinhood “Robin” Padilla: Bismillahir Rahmanir Rahim. Alhamdulillahi Rabbil 'alamin. Panginoon naming nag-iisa, ang nag-iisang hukom, Panginoon ng lahat ng mga daigdig, ang pinakamaawain, ang pinakamahabagin. Panginoon namin, hinihingi po namin ang inyong talino sa oras na ito. Sa oras na ito na ibinigay po sa amin ang pinakamabigat na obligasyon upang makapagbigay ng hustisya. Batid po namin Panginoong Allah na kayo lamang po ang nag-iisang hukom at ang pagiging hukom ay napakabigat na nakalagay po sa aming balikat upang magbigay ng hustisya, hindi lamang po sa mundong ito. kundi ito po ay isang bagay na dadalhin ng aming bayan sa kanyang kasaysayan. Napakabigat po nito, Panginoong Allah, at kayo lamang po ang makapagbibigay sa amin ng lakas ng loob upang magbigay ng tamang justisya sa oras na ito. Amen.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Amen. The Clerk of Court will now call the roll.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Roll call up members, Senator-Judge Aquino, Senator-Judge Cayetano Alan, Senator-Judge Cayetano Pia, Senator-Judge De La Rosa, Senator-Judge Ejercito, Senator-Judge Estrada, Senator-Judge Goh, Senator-Judge Ontiveros, Senator-Judge Lacson, Senator-Judge Lapid, Senator-Judge Legarda, Senator-Judge Marcoleta, Senator-Judge Marcos, senator-judge Padilla, senator-judge Pangilinan, senator-judge Sotto III, senator-judge Tulfo Erwin, senator-judge Tulfo Rafi, senator-judge Villanueva, senator-judge Villar Camil, senator-judge Villar Marc, senator-judge Zubiri, the presiding officer, senator-judge Escudero, Senate President Gatchalian.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: With 19 senator-judges present, the chair declares the presence of a quorum. In accordance with the rules of procedure on impeachment trials, the Chair now recognizes the duly elected Presiding Officer to preside over the proceedings of the Impeachment Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Mr. Senate President. If there are no objections, we shall dispense with the reading of the August 3, 2026 Journal of the Senate, sitting as an Impeachment Court, and shall consider the same as approved.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Bago po tawagin ang presiding officer ang kaso na kabinbin sa impeachment court, may nais lamang po akong sabihin sa ngalan nating lahat.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Magkakaiba man ang ating pananaw at baga man magkakatunggali ang magkabilang panig dito sa impeachment court, may mga bagay-bagay na dapat pinagkakasunduan at pinagkakaisahan natin, lalo na dun sa mga napuya't kagabi kakapanood ng TV. At para sa akin ang isa po dito. Ayan, tagumpay at kampyonato ng ating magaling at magiting na kababayan na si Alex Ayala sa DC Open.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kaya't sa ngalan ng Senado ng mga senator-judges, mga kawanin ng Senado, sa ngalan ng magatong galing mga partido ng impeachment trial, nais po naming ipabatid. Ang aming nagkakaisang pagbati kay Binibining Alex Ayala sa kanyang panalo at kampyonato sa DC Open, tunay na ikinararangal at ipinagbubunyikan naming lahat. Congratulations sa'yo, Alex.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kaya pag may inaantok po na senator-judge,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: malamang nanood kagabi.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The clerk of court is instructed to kindly call the case before this impeachment court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Case number 004-2026 in the matter of impeachment trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Appearances.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Your Honor, same appearance for the prosecution. I understand, Your Honor, that this is a con... Continuation of the direct examination of the prosecution's witness, Atty. Wamil. And with that, Your Honor, may we ask that the counsel for the prosecution, Atty. Lorna Capunan, be recognized.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. At the proper time, yes. Counsel for respondent appearances.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Same appearance for the respondent accused. Good morning, Your Honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Good morning. Before the presiding officer calls on the counsel for the panel of prosecutors, attorney Capunan, for the continuation of his cross and the witness, the chair would like to ask if the respondent, or rather counsel for respondent, has been furnished with a copy of the motion of the panel of prosecutors with respect to the request for judicial notice.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, sir. Yes, that is correct, Your Honors. We were furnished yesterday.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For your information, counsel, we will hear. Your arguments for or against it and or a written opposition or agreement with that motion tomorrow. Just to give you advance information before we start the trial. So do you have enough time?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: At this juncture, Chair, I would now like to recognize with the permission of the Honorable Chua, the prosecutor, rather the counsel for the panel of prosecutors, Attorney Capunan, and Chair instructs the Clerk of Court to bring the witness, Mr. Wamil, before the witness stand.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mr. Wamil, it is understood that you will be continuing with your testimony under the same oath that you had and did yesterday. Do you understand that, sir?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Kapunan, counsel for the panel of prosecutors, you may continue with your direct examination of the witness, Mr. Wamil, of the Commission on Audit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honors.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: To the Senate Impeachment Judges and to the Presiding Officer and Senate President, I beg the indulgence of this honorable court to start this with a recess.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The reason this is necessary, Your Honor, is because yesterday, when prosecution asked for a recess with the permission or consent of the counsel for the respondent, we started to identify and cross-check the 845 acknowledgement receipts. Unfortunately, time ran out and our assisting counsels only were able to show half. Although this court will recall that under Rule 130, Section 3, in coordination with Section 7, we were able to mark a tabulation or a summary prepared personally by this witness, Your Honor, to preempt any possible objection of the respondents and any manifestation that they were not allowed. to compare the copies of our exhibits and their own exhibits as regards the rest of the acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor, unless they will stipulate that there is no need, Your Honor, then it becomes necessary for a brief recess, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, for what purpose is the recess?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, yesterday, when we resumed hearing yesterday, Your Honor, and we were going over these three boxes and... several folders, Your Honor. It had to abruptly stop because we had resumed session. And at that time, our associates noted that kalahati lang po ang natapos sa pag-compare.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, the presiding officer will have a query first beforehand. Yesterday, you presented a summary and a table of his findings based on the 845 acknowledgement receipts contained in the six
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: or three boxes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And you presented some samples.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I count one, two, three, four, five, six, six samples, examples rather. So you mean to say you want to present more acknowledgement receipts as samples as part of the tabulation of the witness?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: No, Your Honor. What we would like to do now and inquire from counsel for the respondent is if it's no longer necessary for your associates to look over the said acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor, if they can manifest that and to preempt any possible technical objection in the future. on their cross-examination or upon offer of this exhibit, Your Honor, because these exhibits will have to be offered in due time. And we do not want it as an objection to the offer that they were not able to compare the rest of the acknowledgement receipts, Your Honor. Now, to preempt that, if counsel is willing to forego with that potential objection, Your Honor, we are ready to proceed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You're talking of only the acknowledgement receipts for the period covering December 21 to December 31, 2022. Yes, Your Honor. Is that what you're referring to? I think I know what counsel-respondent will already say but yes, counsel-respondent, what is your comment on the manifestation of the counsel for the panel of prosecutors?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, we haven't stipulated on anything so I don't see why there's a need to compare actually. We haven't stipulated on anything.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Actually, Attorney Capunan, counsel for the respondent already said yesterday that I'm just subject to cross insofar as the non-stipulated matters is concerned.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That's correct.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The counsel for respondent stipulated on everything you asked for in your list of documents except for that. Except for the acknowledgement receipts for the period covering December 21 to 31, 2022. My understanding, counsel, is that you will be presenting samples from the tabulation or summary of the witness. And as I said, you presented already six. You may proceed to present samples or examples under each category of this table. Without prejudice, however, many they may be subject to your call and discretion given the refusal to stipulate. by the counsel-respondent, which is, of course, they would be well within their rights not to do so, given their own legal theory of the case.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We submit, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So kindly proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With the permission of this honorable court, same appearance, good morning to the senator-judges. Mr. Witness, yesterday, you were able to identify 845 going through these documents, acknowledgement receipts. Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes ma'am. In
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: this 845 acknowledgement receipts which the prosecution marked as exhibits P-1-8-1 up to P-1-8-848, there is a portion there and I will show you a sample on the screen. There is a portion in all of these acknowledgement receipts at
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the bottom thereof. There is a signature in
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the phrase certified true copy.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can we present this witness with a sample acknowledgement receipt?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Assistant counsel may approach from both parties. It's still attorney Peña, right?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I remember.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: His mother will be happy again.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can you go through some of this acknowledgement receipt, Your Honor?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: While counsel is going over... Showing over these acknowledgement receipts to our witness, Mr. Juan Mil,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: we would like to make a manifestation that at the bottom portion of all of these exhibits identified or being identified now by this witness, have the statement certified
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: true copy being shown on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, can you read?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: It's a certified crew copy and there is a name, Davin Bacay. Would you know who this person is?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Who is Mr. Bacay?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Siya po'y admin staff ng Kowa Ikfaw.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kowa Ikfaw. And his signature, there is a signature that appears over the name Davin Bacay. Whose signature is this?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa kanya po. Why do you know?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Davin Bacay po. Nakita ko po siyang pumirma ng ibang dokumento at yung kanyang pirma sa mga dokumentong iyon ay kapares po ng kanyang pirma sa certified true copies.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In all of these acknowledgement receipts that you have seen or saw yesterday,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is it the same bakay that certified as to these photocopies being certified true copies?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, with that, we will proceed where we left off yesterday, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, I believe you were able to identify already the checks and made the witness identify the checks already for the first, second, and third quarter, counsel, if I'm not mistaken.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yesterday, Mr. Witness, we had identified and you had confirmed certain land-bound checks. We will now go to disbursement checks, which you said... Disbursement vouchers, which you said were among the documents submitted by the Office of the Vice President to liquidate, to allegedly liquidate her confidential funds, if shown to you, Mr. Witness. Three disbursement vouchers. And again, with the kind permission of the court and for easy reference of the honorable impeachment judges on screen. And if you please check this copy. Being shown to you, these are stipulated documents, Your Honor, and common exhibits of both the prosecution and the defense. For the prosecution, there is a disbursement voucher dated January 31, 2023, Exhibit P-1-10-B. Shown on the screen.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Likewise, there is a disbursement voucher dated April 10, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-10-C and likewise, the Defense Exhibit. And lastly, disbursement voucher dated July 13, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-10-D.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, sinabi
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the indulgence of counsel, just for the record, the same pieces of evidence identified by the counsel for the panel of prosecutors are also marked, respectively, as D-133-OVP, D-1-57, rather, 30, no, no, 33-OVP, D-1-57-OVP, and D-1-82-OVP for the respondent. Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. Now, Mr. Witness, sinabi mo kahapon na itong mga disbursement vouchers ay sinabmit ng Vice President mismo ng office niya.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Pakisabi sa atin, ano ba ang significance nito mga disbursement vouchers na nakikita natin sa screen?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang significance po ng disbursement voucher na ito, ito po kasi yung mag-initiate nung kanilang pag-process nung cash advance. Dito rin po ang nag-certify yung various signatories nung disbursement voucher.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang disbursement voucher, sinabi mo, dito nag-uumpisa ang proseso?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong proseso yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nang kanilang pag-withdraw po ng kanilang cash advance for the confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Withdrawal ng cash advance, para saan periods? There are three disbursement vouchers shown on the screen and which you have identified. For clarity. Ano ang mga periods na kino-cover nitong disbursement vouchers na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these disbursement vouchers po, ang period covered ay yung first DV, first quarter of 2023, yung second DV, second quarter of 2023, at yung third DV po ay third quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So covered ang tatlong quarters ng confidential funds.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on these documents. We go now to another set.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Oh, there is a signature here.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Here in the middle, there appears a signature being flashed
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: on the screen. Nakalagay certified expense, cash advanced, necessary, lawful, and incurred under my direct supervision. You confirm, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Whose signature is this, if you know?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: This is the signature po of the Vice President, Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And why do you know that this is her signature?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Because the Office of the Vice President submitted po the specimen signatures of the signatories of their documents and included in that submission po is the specimen signature of the Vice President and her signature po on that specimen signature is the same po with her signature on this document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakikita natin yung tatlong signature ng Vice President sa disbursement vouchers na yan. What is the significance of her signature in these three disbursement vouchers kung masasabi mo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, sinertify ni Vice President na yung kanyang cash advances ay kailangan na ayon sa batas at na-include po under her direct supervision.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And ano ang observations mo? dito sa tatlong disbursement vouchers na to.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: With respect lang po dun sa disbursement voucher for the third quarter of 2023, hindi po napirmahan yung box E, which is the receipt of payment portion.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong significance ng observation mo na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ito po kasi yung patunay na na-receive ni kung sino man po yung pay nung cheque, yung payment.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sa pagka-evaluate mo nitong disbursement vouchers na to, ito ba ay compliant sa joint circular na sinabi mo kahapon?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on my evaluation po, wala naman po akong nakitang findings bukod dun sa walang signature yung box E of the third quarter disbursement voucher.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa next set of documents. Tatlo na naman to for the three periods that you mentioned. Showing to you on the screen and please go over the documents being presented by Attorney Pena. There is a liquidation report dated March 29, 2023. Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-9B.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: A liquidation report dated July 11, 2023, which is Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-9C and a liquidation report dated October 23, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-9D. A common exhibit. stipulated by counsel for the respondent yesterday, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Again, with the indulgence of counsel for the panel of prosecutors, for the record and for the easy reference of senator-judges, the three documents referred to by attorney Capunan respectively are marked as well by the respondent as D-1-30-OVP, D-1-55-OVP. D-1-80-OVP. Do you confirm, counsel?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I confirm, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, for the panel of prosecutors, attorney-component, you may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. In the middle of these three liquidation reports, there appears to be an indication, quote-unquote, certified purpose of cash advance duly accomplished. Do you confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And there is a signature, again, appearing on top.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There is a signature appearing thereat. Whose signature is this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: This is the signature of the Vice President, Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you're familiar with this for the same reason, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: what is the significance of the statement, Certified Purpose of Cash Advance, duly accomplished? With the signature of the Vice President appearing in all of these certifications.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, ang significance po noon ay sinertify po ni Vice President na yung purpose nung kanilang CASHA DAT advances ay na-accomplish po nung agency.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And any observations as regards these three documents?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala naman po akong nakitang findings about these liquidation reports po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Just for purposes of clarity, itong three documents are similar to the three periods, the first quarter, the second quarter, and the third quarter months that you earlier mentioned, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong tatlong, this verse, itong tatlong dokumento na nakikita mo dyan, para saang period ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these liquidation reports, yung first liquidation report, ang period covered ay February 6 to March 29, 2023. Yung second liquidation report ay April 25 to June 30, 2023. At yung third liquidation report ay July 14 to September 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Para maalala natin, to remind us, Mr. Witness, for these three quarters,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: of the office of the Vice President for which she submitted liquidation reports. Magkano ang amount ng confidential fund per quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, ang amount ng kanilang quarter Likasya Advance ay 125 million pesos per quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito ba ay fixed amount?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ito ba ay winidron ng buo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa another three sets of documents shown on the screen for easy reference and document being shown to the witness to refresh his memory. We have accomplishment report dated March 30, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-7-B. Likewise, an accomplishment report dated July 11, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-7C, and accomplishment report dated October 9, 2023, Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-7D. Likewise, Your Honor, stipulated documents, common exhibits, both for the prosecution. and the respondent or defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent, would you like to identify for the record the counterpart markings on the part of the respondent?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, Your Honors. On the part of the respondent. Yes, Your Honors. These are marked as Exhibit D-1-74-OVP. D-1-50-OVP and D-1-99-OVP, Your Honor, for the record. Sorry, the first one is actually D-1-50-OVP, the second one would be D-74-OVP, and the third one would be D-1-99-OVP, for the record, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, D-1-50-DE with respect to the 33023 Accomplishment Report, not D-1-21DE.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: For the first quarter, Your Honor, sorry. Yes, Accomplishment Report. For first quarter, it's D-1-5050-OVP, not DE, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Clerk of Court is instructed to kindly correct our records if at all it is different from what the counsel for respondent manifested. Counsel for the panel of prosecutors, attorney-cubo, n'yo may proceed, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. Now, Mr. Witness,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: purposes, para malinawan tayo, ano yung mga periods knocking over ng tatlong accomplishment reports na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Accomplishment report po, ang nakalagay po na period covered ay February 6 to March 29, 2023.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung second accomplishment report po, ang nakalagay na period ay April 25 to June 30, 2023. At yung pangatlo po, July 14 to September 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So tatlong quarters ng Office of the Vice President. Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron dito, common to all of these exhibits, flash on the screen, is the phrase, approved by.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And there is a signature. There
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is a signature there. Whose signature is this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: This is the signature of the Vice President, Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Familiar to you for the same reason, Mr.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And ano ang ibig sabihin ng Nakalagay diyan, approved by, at pinirmahan ng vice president sa tatlong dokumentong ito.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang ibig sabihin po nito ay in-approve niya kung ano man po yung contents nung kanilang quarterly accomplishment reports.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Na-approve ng vice president mismo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, for our appreciation, punta ngayon tayo sa first quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong observations mo? Dito sa nakikita mong first quarter accomplishment report.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this first quarter accomplishment report, meron pong dalawang items dito na hindi kasama dun sa allowable confidential expenses under item 4.8 of the Joint Circular 2015-01.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin ng hindi allowable? Bawal? Bawal ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Opo, kasi yung listahan po nung allowable confidential expenses under 4.8 ng Joint Circular ay exclusive. So kapag hindi po kasama doon, hindi po pwedeng paggabitan ng kanilang confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Aside from itong sinasabi mong bawal na paggamit ng confidential fund appearing in this document, meron ka pa bang ibang observation?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Meron din pong line item for the payment of reward. under item B po nung kanilang actual outcome and accomplishment. At wala po silang sinubmit na any document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer as required po under item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular. So
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: itong linalagay dyan ng payment of reward, ang sinasabi mo, Mr. Witness, based on the Joint Circular, eh... Is this a violation?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am, that is a violation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Why is it a violation again? It is a violation
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: since it is not compliant with the conditions of the payment of reward. which is yung dapat meron po siyang supporting document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account po ng information given by the informant. Sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: lahat ng mga liquidation documents na binigay sa'yo or sinubmit sa office ng COA-ICFAO, wala bang any dokumento na nagpapatunay na ang rewards na binigay sa informant? ay nag-result ng successful activity.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, wala po ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron pa bang observation dito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala na po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa accomplishment report ng second quarter. Exhibit P-1-7C.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Any observations? Ano naman ang masasabi mo dito sa accomplishment report na in-approve mismo ng Vice President Sara Duterte?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Katulad po noon ako ng accomplishment report, meron din po silang line items for provision of medical and food aid at payments of incentive or traveling relative to the confidentiality. Confidential operations na hindi po among the allowable confidential expenses under item 4.8 of the Joint Circular 2015-01.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo na meron nakalagay diyan Medicines. Bakit sinabi mo na bawal o hindi allowed ito sa Joint Circular?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po siya kasama dun sa exclusive list of allowable confidential expenses under item 4.8 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano pa ang na-observe mo dito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Meron din pong line item for the payment of reward for 12 million pesos, pero hindi po siya supportado ng any document evidencing—
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Objection, Your Honor. Objection. I beg the indulgence of— What is the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection of counsel?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, I gave some leeway earlier to the witness, but we move to strike out the answer of the witness as far as the payment of reward is concerned. Kasi yung pinag-uusapan lang naman natin dito, on its face, kung merong mali. So utilization of confidential intelligence funds in terms of the accomplishment report. He is now going into the findings, which is not part and parcel of this form, which is the accomplishment report, Your Honor. Not yet, part of it. Not yet. So what I'm saying is the payment of reward by itself is not a violate. Indicating the payment of reward here by itself is not a violation of the Joint Circular, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Because we are not yet, if at all, at the AOM level and or not just as well. Kindly reform, counsel. Objection sustained.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Is this payment of rewards included in the so-called allowable expense of confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on item 4.8, yes, subject to the three conditions as enumerated.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What are these three conditions?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular, payment of rewards must be made to informers who must be non-employees of the agency concerned, subject first to the approval of the head of the agency, second to the submission of documents evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account given by the informer, and thirdly, it must be directly related to the confidential operation. At sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: mga requirements na sinabing mo, compliant ba ang Office of the Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, hindi po sila nag-submit ng any document evidencing the success po of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Before we proceed to the third quarter and your further observations dito sa second quarter, magkano ba? Ang sinabi na amount na ginamit sa confidential funds para sa medicines.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question po? What quarter po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Magkano ba? If you know. Kasi ikaw nag-evaluate. Magkano ba ang ginastos para sa medicines?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For what quarter po ma'am? Sorry. For the second quarter. For the second quarter. Based on this accomplishment report po, Yung provision of medical and food aid ay nagkaka-amount po ng 40 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano ulit?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based po on this accomplishment report, yung provision of medical and food aid ay 40 million pesos po yung amount.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa first quarter naman,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: meron bang entry dyan na nakalagay medicines?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Meron pong entry dito for provision of medical and food aid for 40 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Forty million pesos.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Forty-two
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Forty-two million pesos ang nakalagay diyan ngayon.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: accomplishment report na yan, meron bang inattach ang Office of the Vice President? First and second quarter na inidentify. Meron ba siyang inattach mga dokumento na nagpapatunay? na ginastos talaga yung 42 million na yan for the first quarter and 10 million na yan for the second quarter for medicines alone, Mr. Witness. Meron bang attachment itong accomplishment report na sinubmit?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: silang inattach na any document po supporting yung kanilang payment for medicine.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Earlier, minention mo, meron ring gastos for traveling. Magkano naman yun, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For what quarter, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter muna.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the first quarter po, yung kanilang payment of incentives or traveling relative to confidential operations ay 10 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 10 million pesos. At again, tanong ko, sa expense na 10 million na yan for traveling expenses, meron bang inattach na mga annexes? Diyan, para explain, pa paano ginastos sa travel ang 10 million? May mga... attachments ba yung accomplishment report na yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang in-attach.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi na-explain itong 10 million, Mr. Witness? Walang official receipts attached? Meron ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala pong official receipts na-attach.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Any other observations sa second quarter?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: There
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: you go, okay.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Same lang po with the first quarter, yung findings pa dito.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa third quarter naman po tayo pumunta. Exhibit P-1-17-7-D. What are your observations? Ano naman ang masasabi mo dito sa accomplishment report ng Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Meron din po silang payment of reward dito na worth 35 million pesos.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pero wala po silang inattach na any document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sinabi mo na walang sinubmit na ebidensya. Wala bang naka-attach dito sa accomplishment report?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Walang report on success of the surveillance activity?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And, sa pagkaalam mo, and based on your evaluation of the provisions of the Joint Circular compliance audit ito? Compliant ba ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po siya compliant.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Dahil wala nga pong supporting document po yung kanilang payment of rewards as required under item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo 4.8 ng Joint Circular. Ito ba yung pinakita mo sa impeachment court kahapon? yung 4.8 na yan.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung provision? Isa po siya sa pinakita ka po. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, magkano naman? Magkano yung item na yan sa third quarter report?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the third quarter po, ang amount ng kanilang payment of rewards ay 35 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 35 million pesos. Para sa isang quarter lang?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para sa third quarter. Thank you, Mr. Witness. Punta naman tayo. sa next set of documents na sinabmit rin ng Office of the Vice President para iliquidate yung kanyang confidential funds for the first, second, and third quarter. I refer you now, flashed on the screen and being shown to you, are certifications submitted by the Office of the Vice President. Unang-una, certification of the Office of the Vice President dated March 30, 2023, Exhibit P-1-6-B. Pangalawa, OVP certification dated July 11, 2023, which is Prosecutions Exhibit P-1-6-C. At pangatlo, OVP certification dated October 9, 2023, Exhibit P. 1-6-D for the prosecution stipulated upon by the respondent and likewise part of their defense exhibits.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, we confirm, Your Honor, and we would like to manifest that for the first quarter certification that is marked as exhibit D-1-34-OVP, second quarter That is Exhibit D-1-58-OVP. And for the third quarter, it's D-1-83-OVP for the defense, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And your documents are certified through copies, counsel, respondent. That is correct, Your Honor. Counsel for the panel of prosecutors may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. Now, please look at these certifications. Meron nakalagay dyan sa bottom ng page, Attested. Anong ibig sabihin ng attested?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang ibig sabihin po nung attested ay vinerify at could confirm po as true nung signatory dito yung contents nung certification.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sino naman ang signatory na nakikita natin sa dokumentong ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this certification po si Vice President Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At siya mismo ang nag-attest na tama lahat ang nakalagay dyan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you are familiar with the signature for the same reason, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang mga observations ang masasabi mo tungkol sa tatlong dokumentong ito? Incidentally, Mr. Witness, what periods did this cover, again, for the record?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, yung for the first quarter, yung February 6 to March 29. 2023, 42nd quarter, April 25 to June 30, 2023, and 43rd quarter, July 14 to September 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang masasabi mo? Ano naman ang observations mo sa tatlong dokumentong ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Since these are pro forma documents po, wala naman po akong nanote ng observations with these certifications.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin ng pro forma? Parang copy-paste?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Naka-attach po siya as annex doon sa Joint Circular 2015-01. Naka
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: -attach sa Joint Circular at yun ang sinyamit nila?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Naka-annex po. Yung
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: format. Ang tawag doon ay?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Proforma po. Naka-annex yung format doon sa Joint Circular 2015-01. Ang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: tawag ko doon, copy-paste na copy-paste. Anyway. Your Honor,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: we, again. With all due respect to opposing counsel, I would like to object
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: to
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: that characterization, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: withdraw, Your Honor. I just could not resist myself. Now, provisions of the Joint Circular. Sinabi mo ito yung pinagbasihan mo ng mga evaluation mo ng mga documents na to. What, if any, are the violations that you observe based on the Joint Circular?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: May I clarify po kung anong document po yung piniportay niyo ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa lahat ng dokumento.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa lahat po ng dokumento. Based on, for what quarter po? Sorry.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For all the quarters.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For all the quarters. Yung first and second quarter po kasi magkasama sa isang AOM lang and then yung third quarter ay nakaseparate po yung AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, punta muna tayo sa first and, sinasabi mo, Mr. Witness, na yung first and second quarter, eh, isa lang ang na-issue na AOM. Ano itong ibig sabihin ulit ng AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Audit Observation Memorandum po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: On the Joint Circular 2015-01, yung Audit Observation Memorandum po ay yung written notification to the agency informing them of the deficiencies noted during the audit and requiring them to submit an explanation or the documents being sought po dun sa AOM or both.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, under the circular, this Joint Circular that you mentioned, ito bang Audit Observation Memorandum? Kailan ini-issue ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ini-issue po siya upon evaluation po nung auditor nung documents at may nanote po siyang findings based on the evaluation po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Parang meron tayong konting background, no? Kasi kahapon, meron ring na-stipulate ang respondent at ang prosecution ng mga notice of suspension at notice of disallowance for the better appreciation of this honorable court. Pakieducate kami. Pakisabi nga anong difference ng AOM, Audit, Observation, Memorandum,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: pagkatapos yung Notice of Suspension, at pagkatapos yung Notice of Disallowance. Ano ang mga pagkakaiba nitong tatlo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: If I am to start with the definitions based on the joint circular, katulad nung na-define ko kanina sa AOM, it is a written notification to the agency concerned of the deficiencies noted during the audit and requiring them to submit an explanation or the documents being sought or bought. At ang agency po ay merong 15 days from the receipt of the AOM within which to submit their comments, justifications, or documents as required in the AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So pagkatapos ng issuance ng isang audit, observation, memorandum, ang mga subject ng audit ay binibigyan ng 15 days para mag-submit ng mga dokumento?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based po dun sa Rules and Regulations on Settlement of Accounts po ng COA. Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Paano pag may sinubmit na dokumento at hindi pa rin sapat or tama or insufficient or may discrepancy, anong nangyayari?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag may sinubmit po na document at based on the evaluation of the auditor, hindi pa rin po sapat yung document na yon, then that is the time po na mag-i-issue na po ng notice of suspension. Itong
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: anong definition ng notice of suspension sa Joint Circular?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under the joint circular po, yung notice of suspension is a written notification to the agency head and the accountant informing them of the temporary disallowance po nung disbursement sa audit because it appears that the disbursement is irregular, illegal, or improper and requiring them to submit their justifications or the documents po being sought in the AOM or both.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo, Mr. Witness, para maintindihan natin, ito ay temporary.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on findings na irregular. Ano ba irregular? Ano yung ibig sabihin ng irregular?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on COA circulars po, ang irregular disbursement ay yung mga disbursement na hindi umaayon or hindi nagkocomply dun sa requirements ng mga COA issuances.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sa Pilipino, ang tawag dito ay irregular pa rin. Tama.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong illegal. Illegal. Anong ibig sabihin ng illegal?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag sinabi pong illegal, yung disbursement po ay hindi nagkocomply dun sa applicable laws.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At kung sinabi mong improper?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag improper naman po, ang ibig sabihin yung expenses ay either unnecessary, excessive, extravagant, or unconscionable.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So pag nagbigay kayo ng notice of suspension, Ito ay nagpapahayag. This means ang significance nito ay naobserve ninyo, ikaw, sa audit findings mo na ito ay irregular, illegal, or improper.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Leading, Your Honor. Objection. I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: will
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: go to the next question. Pag hindi na-comply ang notice of suspension, what action, if any, is taken by your office?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag hindi po na-comply yung notice of suspension, then that is the time po na mag-i-issue na kami ng notice of disallowance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman itong notice of disallowance?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the Joint Circular po, yung notice of disallowance ay yung written notification to the agency head and the accountant informing them of the disallowance noong disbursement and requiring them to restitute the amount po nung disbursement because yung disbursement ay illegal, improper, or irregular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, Mr. Witness, whether tinatawag mo ito AOM or audit observation memorandum or whether notice of suspension or whether notice of disallowance. In these three stages, nabibigyan ng opportunity ang inu-audit na agency para mag-comply? Yun po ba ang ibig sabihin ng explanation mo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag sa AOM po, tsaka notice of suspension, yes, binibigyan po silang ng opportunity para mag-comply. Pero kapag ND na po kasi, pag notice of disallowance, ang tangi remedy na lang nila is to settle the amount or to appeal with the commission proper.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Let us go now to the issue of the Office of the Vice President. Earlier, you said AOMs were issued to the Office of the Vice President. Correct? Now,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: specifically,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: let us go now to the first and second quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Showing to you, and if shown to you, and flashed on the screen, would you be able to identify the same?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, for purposes of identification, this again is a stipulated common exhibit. This AOM, dated February 1, 2024, corresponding to the first and second quarters, have
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: been identified as Exhibit P-1-12-E for the prosecution.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor. And a part of the defense, this was pre-marked as D-1-105-OVP for the information of the Honorable Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Attorney Caponan, may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please look at this AOM and refresh your memory. What, Mr. Witness, did you observe from this AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung findings po or observations namin, una po, Hindi po nagsubmit ng documentary evidence of payments si OBP for the first and second quarters of 2023.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pangalawa po, based on their accomplishment report, meron kasing nakalagay as payment of rewards, pero wala pong sinubmit si OBP na any document evidencing the success po, which is in violation of the item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, for the better appreciation, Your Honor, and with your permission, this is being Flashed on the screen, the findings made are in boxed in red. So yung second finding mo, una, ulitin natin.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung una po ay walang sinubmit na documentary evidence of payment si OBP for the first and second quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano pa?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pangalawa po, dahil may line item for the payment of rewards sa kanilang accomplishment report. Wala po silang sinamit na any document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer in violation po noong item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron mga, before you go to your next observation, Mr. Witness, meron mga amounts stated dyan. For the record, can you read these amounts and what periods they correspond to? In terms of payment of rewards.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this AOM po, yung 15 million pesos ay binayad as payment of reward noong February 6 to March 29, 2023. At yung 12 million pesos naman po ay binayad as reward noong April 25 to June 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And nakalagay dito, nakalagay, non-compliant with item 4.8 from item 4.8.5.b of the Joint Circular. Why is this non-compliant based on your submissions in your AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung item 4.8.5.b po kasi, yun yung documentary evidence o yung document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities. Pero since wala po silang sinamit na document na yun, hindi po nag-comply yung kanilang payment of rewards doon sa requirements ng Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para maintindihan natin, kasi medyo technical to, ano yung evidence of success? Ano ang kinoconsider ng office mo na evidence of success?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Actually, based dun po sa Joint Circular, walang any specific document na na-mention. Pero kasi ang tinitignan po namin is dapat merong causal link yung... surveillance, yung successful surveillance activity or information gathering at saka yung information given by the informer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba confidential itong information na rinirequiring? Confidential ba ito? Yung tinatawag mo na causal. Cause at saka effect.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi ba yan? Is that confidential information?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Since yun po yung requirement ng Joint Circular, kailangan po nilang i-comply po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Necessary ba ang... Ano ang... I will refine. Next question, Mr. Witness. There is a box here in paragraph 3. What is this all about?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: What box po? The one
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: being shown?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano ang nakalagay dito, nakalagay sa paragraph 3 that the amount with reference to medicine and food aid? Please look at your notes.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And tell us the significance of these findings.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang nakalagay po dito sa number 3 na merong items for the provision of medical and food aid at payment of incentives for traveling relative to the confidential operations ng agency doon sa kanilang first and second quarter accomplishment reports.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron mga amounts indicated dito. Pakibasa.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. For the accomplishment report for the period February 6 to March 29, 2023,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa provision of medical and food aid po, ang nagasos nila ay 42 million pesos. Tapos sa accomplishment report for the April 25 to June 30, 2023, yung nagasos po nila for the provision of medical and food aid ay 40 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ang total nito, Mr. Witness, para sa period na to ay 42 million plus 40 million.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 82. Million, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submission po, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on their submissions, did they also attach to their submissions any documents showing or proving payments for medical supplies or food supplies?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, meron pang ibang figures dito, pakibasa, and what are they for?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung isa naman po, yung February 6 to March 29 period, 10 million po yung binayad for the payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations. At for the period naman po na April 25 to June 30, 2023, may binayad po na another 10 million for the payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So sa binasa mo, ang total nito ay 20 million?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At itong 20 million ba may kasamang mga resibo or attachments? para patunayan na nagastos tong 20 million para sa travel.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, wala pong inattach si OBP.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. And sa last sentence, ano itong amount na 20 million pesos?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ayan po yung total po nung kanilang payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations for the first and second quarter po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ngayon, meron kang conclusion sa last paragraph.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can you read it?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The provision of medical and food aid and payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations expenses do not fall among those enumerated under item 4.8 of the Joint Circular. Thus, the same should not be charged against the confidential fund of the agency.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sinasabi mo ang nature ng listahan sa Joint Circular ay ano?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Exclusive po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Exclusive. Anong ibig sabihin ng exclusive? Bawal ang wala sa listahan. Tama ba yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Another box item is paragraph number 4. Please refer to your notes as shown on the screen. Anong significance if any nitong finding mo sa AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under number 4 po, hindi po... naka-indicate sa kanilang physical and financial plan yung specific confidential activities na kanilang paggagamitan po nung kanilang pondo in violation of the item 4.2 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Itong physical and financial plan, eh, identified to, stipulated document ito, tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ngayon, ano ba dapat pag tinitignan ng isang physical and financial plan? Ano ba ang hinahanap dyan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kasama
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ba dyan? Sakop ba niyan ang Christmas party?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Paulit po ng tanong.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasama ba sa physical and financial plan ang Christmas party?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung agency po ang makakapag-answer niyan. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasama ba dyan? Yung
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: physical and financial plan po kasi ginagamit nila to support their allocation. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasama ba dyan tree planting?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: It is not... It is outside po my authority to... answer that since agency lang po ang makakasagot niya.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasama ba dyan ang magbibigay ka ng awards? In the nature of your definition of confidential funds, are these activities considered confidential activities?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: As an answer, Your Honors, it is beyond the witness authority to determine.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If he knows, Your Honor, he's competent. He's a competent witness. He's the one who personally evaluated and he's also a lawyer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer if he knows. Mr. Ramel, you may answer if you know.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: If I am to relate po yung sinabi n'yo dun sa item 4.8 of the Joint Circular, hindi po kasama yung mga binanggit n'yo dun sa allowable expenses po ng Confidential Fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Mr. Rudners. Punta naman tayo sa itong
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: AOM, Audit Observation Memorandum. Ang exhibit number ay, for the record, P-1-12-E. Mr. Counsel, for the respondent. This is a common exhibit.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Already stipulated and the counterpart exhibit marking by the respondent was already given for the record.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: After receiving... Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor, may we just clarify if we're referring to the first quarter AOM?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: She's referring to the respondent's D-1-105-OVP. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, for clarity's sake, the first and second quarters are covered by only one... audit observation memorandum which this witness just testified on.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, counsel. The counsel for respondent confirms that. The presiding officer confirms that as well.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The other liquidation documents, Mr. Witness, were submitted to you for the
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: office of the Vice President. We now go to the third quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: findings on liquidation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness. What were your findings? Because this covers the first and second quarter. Ano naman ang findings mo tungkol sa third quarter ng Office of the Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa third quarter cash advance and liquidation ng Office of the Vice President, ang naging findings po doon ay una, hindi nagsubmit si Office of the Vice President ng kanilang documentary evidence of payments para sa kanilang third quarter liquidation which is violation po noong item 4.12 of the Joint Circular. Yung kanilang accomplishment report ay merong payment of reward. Pero hindi po siya substantiated ng any document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer, which is in violation of the item 4.8.5b of the Joint Circular. At pangatlo po, Your Honor, may I be allowed to refer to the AOM for the complete
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: enumeration
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: of the findings?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May the witness refer to his notes to refresh
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: his
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: memory.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: May we just clarify on this matter?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, what is the comment of counsel, correspondent?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yesterday, I remember that the witness was only in ICFAO until February 2024. Is that correct? May we check the record if that is correct?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, 2014 to 2024. That's what he said.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay, so this AOM for the third quarter was issued August 8, 2024, Your Honor. So he is referring to something that he has no personal knowledge of?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What month did you leave Kowa Ikfaw, Mr. Ramil?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: February of 2024, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, this is preliminary. We would have, if we were allowed to continue with this questioning, Your Honor. that this witness will attest to the fact that he was the one. Before he left, he drafted. He prepared a draft of an AOM for the third quarter. And if I may be allowed, maybe counsel will see the relationship of my question to this AOM. Then
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness, kindly not refer to an AOM. If indeed you prepared a draft, as you will testify on later, you can refer to your notes, but not... My
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: apologies, Your Honor. Do you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: have notes pertaining to the draft you prepared pertaining to the supposed AOM issued after you left COA Iqfaw?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I don't have my notes with me. Pero I can give po yung the additional audit observation based on my draft po na sinamit sa Iqfaw.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: May we see the draft, Your Honor? Do
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: you have a copy of the draft,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mr. Wamil?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I do not have the copy of the draft with me. Nasa file po siya ng ICPAO.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, attorney kapunan, do you have a copy of the draft? Will you be marking it?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: No, Your Honor. We are not marking a draft. We are just eliciting... From this witness' testimonial evidence that before he left, he did prepare a draft which he turned over to his successor in the position, Your Honor. And this will be testified to by our next witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But witness is not allowed by the court to refer to the AOM issued after he already left the office. If he did not bring his notes, then he cannot refer to any other document while he is testifying.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Subject to those
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: conditions, counsel may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, we have finished with the Office of the Vice President for the last quarter of 2022, the first, second, and third quarter, and all the liquidation reports submitted by the respondent Vice President to the COA ICFAO Office, Your Honor. We will now go to the Department of Education.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For this, Your Honor, can I ask for a one-minute recess so I can confer? Just one minute, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: One
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: minute recess is granted. For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the panel of prosecutors,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Gabunan may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. We now go to the Department of Education. And, Mr. Witness, I will refer you to three quarters. Quarter 1, Quarter 2, and Quarter 3 for 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, again, to refresh your memory, what periods do these quarters cover? We are now talking about the Department of Education.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions to the ICPAO, yung first quarter po, ang coverage po noon ay February 20 to March 30,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 2023. Yung second quarter po ay April 20... to June 29, 2023 at yung third quarter po ay July 12 to September 29, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. And the Department of Education, Mr. Witness, please confirm whether or not they submitted documents by way of liquidation for their confidential funds.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. They submitted them.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And can you refresh your memory? How much did the Department of Education receive?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang kanilang confidential fund po for each quarter ay 37.5 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 37.5 million? A fixed amount?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. Per quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And were these amounts withdrawn in full?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. Based
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: on the
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: documents po na binigay nila sa amin.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Let us now go to these documents that you said were submitted to your office. Who submitted this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The Department of Education.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, if you are shown one of these documents, which is a physical financial plan for the first to the third quarter of 2023, furiously marked as exhibits P-1-18-A-3,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 1-18-A-B and P-1-14-B. For easy reference, Your Honor, this document stipulated and common exhibit also with the defense, Your Honor, is being shown to the witness and flashed on the screen.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Correct, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: On the part of the respondent?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: On the part of the respondent, these are Exhibits D-1-2-DE, D-1-50-DE, and D-1-74-DE.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Seventy-four, not seventy-nine.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Seventy-four, Your Honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Witness, these documents that you're seeing now, there is an annotation approved by
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What does approved by mean?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang ibig sabihin po ng approved by ay in-approve po nung signatory dito sa box na ito yung contents of the physical and financial plan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And this is in all three documents, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There appears to be a signature in these three documents. Whose signature are these?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Assisting counsel for both parties may approach the witness and compare the documents they possess.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Please go over these documents and tell us whose signature is this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Signature po ni Vice President Sara Duterte po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you're familiar with this signature for the same reason she stated, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What does a signature of the Secretary, and
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: here it is the signature of the Vice President, concurrently Secretary of Education, Sara Duterte. What does this signature attest to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang karulat po nung nasabi ko kanina, yung signature niya po rito, ang ibig sabihin ay in-approve niya po yung contents nung physical and financial plan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I am showing to you now, Mr. Witness, a document which is for the third quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And this is part, as we can see on the screen, this is a part of Exhibit P-1-14-B. Please, for the record, tell
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: us your observations for
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the third quarter, for the first, second, and third quarter as appearing in this exhibit and in the notes or the documents you are looking at.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: That is here. Can you read?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Physical target. Can you read the first column?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: this is a quick interjection, again with the due indulgence and I think the patience of opposing counsel, but if we're talking about the third quarter physical and financial plan, I just wanted to confirm that you were still there when you received these documents, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That's all. It
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: was submitted July 3,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: 2023. Yes, I just wanted to confirm that.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Counsel for the panel of prosecutors, attorney Kapunan, you may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What observations have you made or did you make as regards the first quarter submission in the physical and financial plan of the DepEd?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Doon sa kanilang physical and financial plan for the first quarter, hindi po naka-indicate yung kanilang specific. confidential activities na pagbabasayan po ng kanilang disbursement from the confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakalagay sa first column, counterinsurgency programs. Did the DepEd submit any evidence on this or documents evidencing what it claims to be expenditures on counterinsurgency programs?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, wala po silang silamit na document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And it says here, what was the outcome expected from this? If you can read for the record.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, for the counterinsurgency program, ang expected outcome po ay to prevent any recruitment by the NPA and other communists and left these groups towards teachers and students.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And, Mr. Witness, with this submission, did the DepEd, Department of Education, submit? Any list of NPAs, communist or leftist groups?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submissions po, wala naman po silang siramit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And the next column, a target to eliminate or reduce recruitment of teachers and learners by communist or leftist groups. Any observation on this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Since hindi po naka-enumerate yung kanilang specific confidential activities, hindi po naka-match yung kanilang physical target on the specific confidential activities na paggagamitan nila ng kanilang fund from confidential. There
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: was no list of teachers, no list of learners, nor list of communist or leftist groups appended to any of the documents submitted by the DepEd, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For emphasis, please read the amount here.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The amount po is 9,375,000 pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We go as well to the second quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What observations can you make about the second quarter, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Same po with the first quarter, hindi rin po naka-indicate yung kanilang specific confidential activities na kanilang paggagamitan ng Magiging basis po ng kanilang disbursements from the confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Same observation for the third quarter in terms of physical target. Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And the amount, please state for the record. For the second quarter, to eliminate, reduce recruitment of teachers and learners by communist groups or leftist groups. A function of the DepEd. How much was spent by the DepEd for this function?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the second quarter po, 9.3 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And for the third quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the third quarter, 9.2 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, we go now to the second program or activity allegedly conducted by the DepEd. abuse prevention and control within schools. Mr. Witness, were any documents submitted to show what activities these programs allegedly to prevent abuse and control within schools with the expected objective of reducing abuses against learners did the DepEd? submit any documents as to list of schools or list of learners or list of or number of abuses. Based on
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: their submission po, wala po silang sinubmit na document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And the third column says, increase community participation in reporting cases against learners. You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the same is true for the second quarter and the third quarter, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. How
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: much was spent on this activity to increase community participation for the first quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the first quarter po, 10 million pesos. And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the second quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the second quarter, 10 million 75 thousand pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And for the third quarter, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 10,125,000 pesos po. And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: for this community participation, totaling for the three quarters, 30 million. Meron bang listahan ng mga communities kung saan na-increase ang participation nila para sa reporting ng abuses ng mga kabataan? May listahan ba na sinubmit ang DepEd dito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang sinubmit na listahan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para sa tatlong quarters, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Punti naman tayo dito sa number 3.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakalagay dito, anti-illegal activities, operations. Anong meron bang listahan na binigay ang DepEd? Kung ano-ano itong anti-illegal activities, operations?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submission po, wala po silang binigay na listahan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong nakalagay na illegal activities within schools, may listahan ba ng skwelahan? na binigay?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang binigay na listahan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May linagay ba na ano-ano ang tinatawag ng DepEd na illegal activities?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pwedeng paulit po ng tanong.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung mga activities na sinabi dito sa exhibit, may listahan ba kung ano yung illegal activities na gustong eliminate ng DepEd?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang binigay na listahan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa third column, nakalagay, increase and heightened conduct of surveillance activities to prevent illegal activities. Again, Mr. Witness, may listahan ba or document ang sinubmit ng DepEd para patunayan na ginastos nga ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang sinubmit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And your observation is likewise the same, Mr. Witness, for the second and third quarters?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Walang submission na binigay.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pakibasa ang amounts involved dito. For the first quarter, ang amount ay?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Anong item po, ma'am? Number 3?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Number 3, yung tinatawag na anti-illegal activities, operations. Magkano? Kanong ginastos ng DepEd?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the first quarter po, 9 million pesos. For the second quarter, 9.1 million pesos. And for the third quarter, 9,140,000 pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano ang arithmetic nun? 9 times... Almost 30
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: million. 27
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ,240
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ,000 pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 27 million na wala namang kasamang document para sabihin kung ano yung mga... illegal activities na yan. Lastly, Mr. Witness, anti-extremism at terrorism programs.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Extremism and terrorism programs ng DepEd? Anong ibig sabihin nito? Nakalagay dito sa second column. Pakibasa. Your Honor, we'll object to
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: the question, anong ibig sabihin? Because obviously this is something submitted by the DepEd and the witness is not competent enough to testify what DepEd meant.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, I was just reading it. In fact, there is no question on what is this.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Then I apologize for that. I just heard, anong ibig sabihin?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We need rope na yun, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa second column, gather information necessary for the implementation of general peace and order. Peace and order within the department.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron bang sinubmit na documents dito, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Anong document po ulit yan, Ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong nakalagay dito, to gather information necessary for the implementation of general peace and order within The department. Tama bang basa ko? Hindi within the country. Within their own department.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What documents were submitted to evidence this information gathered?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang sinamit na document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Last please. Intensify. Next column. Intensify background investigation of DepEd personnel and learners involved. terrorist groups sa campus, involved in terrorist groups. Mr. Witness, any evidence of this intensification? Pinatibay daw ang background information kasi daw merong terrorist groups sa mga skwelahan. Ano naman ang dokumentong sinubmit ng DepEd para patunayan? Natunay nga na may terrorist ang mga eskwelahan. Meron ba? Submit the documents?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang sinubmit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And this is the same for the second quarter and the third quarter. You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the record, what are the amounts spent allegedly?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Magkano'ng ginastos ng DepEd para mawalan ng terrorist ang mga eskwelahan? 9 million, correct?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter, can you read?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents submitted po, for the counterinsurgency program, 9,375,000 pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the second quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the second quarter, 9.3 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And for the third quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 9.2 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And, pakibasa. Basahin mong lahat.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the number two, yung abuse prevention.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Total. I'm sorry. Sa second quarter, nasabi mo na?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you clarify your question po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter, sinabi mo, 9,125,000. Second quarter, magkano?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 9
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: .3
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And for the third quarter?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 9.2 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang total, anong significance nito? Pag in-addition mo lahat,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: First quarter, second quarter, third quarter, at lahat ng activities na sinabi dito na wala naman dokumento, aba, 37 million pumatak per quarter. You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the document po, yung total po ay 37.5 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: A fixed amount.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Per quarter. A
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: fixed amount for the first quarter, 37.5, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Another fixed amount for the second quarter?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Another fixed amount for the third quarter.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sina naman ang pirmirma dito? Again, Mr. Witness, na nakalagay approved by?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang nakapirma po dito ay si Vice President Sara Duterte po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And that is her signature?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Which you are familiar with for the same reason you said earlier.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We now go to three liquidation documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: which are land bank checks. Again, stipulated to by this by the counsel for the respondent. These are land bank checks number 00000453 dated February 20, 2023. Exhibit P-1-20-A. Another land bank check, 000000964, dated April 19, 2023. And another land bank check, number 0000002250, dated 11 July, 2023. Marked by prosecution, respectively, as Exhibit P-1-20-A. P-1-20-B and P-1-20-C being flashed on the screen and shown by Atty. Peña to the witness. For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the record, counsel, respondent, these are your exhibits. What again for the record?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: For the check ending 0453 dated February 20, 2023, Your Honors, that was marked as exhibit D-1- For the check dated July 11,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: 2023, check ending number 2250, that is exhibit D-1-57-DE. And for the other check ending 0964, dated April 19, I believe, 2023, this is D-1-27-DE, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Correct. Duly noted. Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank you, Your Honor. Now, tell us, Mr. Witness, ano naman ang significance ditong mga tatlong land bank checks na nakalagay dito sa screen at na-examine mo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang significance po nung land bank checks na ito ay ito po yung proof na pwede nilang i-withdraw yung kanilang cash advances po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And anong periods covered?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents po na na-mention, na pakita earlier, for the first quarter, ang period covered po ay February 20 to March, may I refer po to the documents for the period po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may do so with respect to the, you're referring to the physical and financial plan. I'm
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: to the ano po. Or
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to the check. Not the
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: check. To the land bank checks, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No, the question, counsel, is for what period does it cover? It's not in the check.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What periods do these three checks cover?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po. For the first quarter, po, since wala
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: pong nakalagay dito sa checks na period covered, po, ma'am. Pero yung first check, po, is for the first quarter 2023. Yung next check, po, is for the second quarter 2023 and for the yung third check, po, is for the third quarter of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We now go to the next set of liquidation documents. And you will be shown disbursement voucher dated January 31, 2023, disbursement voucher dated April 19, 2023, and disbursement voucher dated 11 July 2023, successively marked as Exhibit P-1-19A. Exhibit P-1-19B and Exhibit P-1-19C for the prosecution stipulated exhibits, Your Honor, with
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the defense.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: On the part of the respondent?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: On the part of the respondent, it is Exhibit D-1-5-DE, Exhibit D-1-29-DE. And the last one, Your Honor, is Exhibit D-1-58-DE.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Attorney Gabonan, may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, for what periods were these disbursement vouchers given for?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these disbursement vouchers po, yung una po ay for the first quarter of 2023. Yung pangalawa ay second quarter of 2023 at yung pangatlo po, hindi
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po nakalagay kung anong specific quarter po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, Mr. Witness, you have gone over this document and it's being flashed on the screen for easy reference of the impeachment court. Any observations that you may have with regards to these three disbursement vouchers?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Itong disbursement vouchers po na ito ay in-approve. Ni Undersecretary Annalyn M. Sevilla in violation po noong Joint Circular na ang nakalagay po ay the head of the agency shall be responsible for the approval of the cash advances.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sine naman tong pumirma?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these disbursement vouchers po si Undersecretary Annalyn M. Sevilla.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Again, why is this a violation?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Dahil under the Joint Circular po, it is the responsibility of the head of the agency to approve the cash advances.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And who is the head of the DepEd?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The head po of DepEd during the period covered by these cash advances po ay si Vice President Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There appears a signature in each of these three documents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Who? Whose signature are these, if you know?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ito po ay mga pirma ni Vice President Sara Duterte.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And... Significantly, Mr. Witness, it says here, Vice President of the Philippines and Secretary of Education. You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document, yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the first quarter. The second quarter also is above the inscription, Vice President of the Philippines and Secretary of Department of Education. You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And for the third quarter, it is signed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Signature which you identified is above the annotation, Vice President and Secretary of the Department of Education. Mr. Witness, confirming this?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what is the significance, Mr. Witness, of the Vice President? concurrently DepEd secretaries. Signature to these three documents.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sinertify po ni Vice President Sara Duterte as the Secretary of Education na yung cash advances po ay kailangan na ayon sa batas at incurred po under her direct supervision.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can you read from your copy? And it's flashing the screen. Yung particulars nito, above For the first document, above the signature of the Vice President, concurrently Secretary of Education. Pakibasa kasi.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: What particular box po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasi, the first, this first document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The one that says particulars and is above. Pakibasa kasi ang dilim, hindi ko makita.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Particulars: first quarter CY 2023 cash advance payment of allotments under the maintenance and other operating expenses authorized under page 376 of RA No. 11936, the General Appropriations Act, fiscal year 2023, and Section 85, page 778, of the General Provisions, FY 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Itong binasa mo ng particulars, ito ba ay
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Or
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: relating to confidential funds, yung certification na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po naka-indicate dito na yung kanilang disbursement ay for the confidential fund of the debit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kung alam mo, what is it for?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, ang nakalagay ay payment of allotments under the MOOE.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anong ibig sabihin ng MOOE? Anong ibig sabihin nun? Kung hindi ito confidential funds, ano naman itong MOOE na pinaggamitan ng pera na confidential funds ng Vice President kum Secretary of Education?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung MOOE po kasi kasama yun doon sa kanilang regular funds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Regular funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang regular funds ba, pakiexplain lang sa akin from a layman's point of view. Ano ang regular funds at ano ang confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung regular funds po ng agency, yun yung kanilang pondo na ginagamit nila for their operations. Operations and yun po. Well, yung confidential fund po, ito po yung specific lump sum ng agency which is to be used for their confidential operations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At pareho rin ang annotation dito? sa second disbursement voucher at third disbursement voucher, Mr. Witness, na ito ay patunay na dinisberse ang mga pondo para sa confidential funds para sa operational expenses.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pwede pong paulit po ng tanong?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ang sinasabi ko, I will reform. So itong disbursement voucher, na nakalagay dito, sinabi mo, when asked, you explain that this appears to be, ito nakalagay dito, ay liquidation ng expenses na hindi naman para sa liquidation ng confidential funds. Kasi confidential to ng regular funds niya, tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ah, disbursement voucher pa lang po ito. Disbursement voucher pa lang po itong document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Disbursement voucher, I'm sorry, disbursement voucher. na sinasubmit para liquidating document para sa confidential fund? Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: It is one of the documents submitted to support the liquidation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At you confirm na nakalagay dito operational expenses?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents, maintenance and other operating expenses.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Maintenance and other operational expenses. Yung maintenance and other operational expenses ba ay? nasa listahan kung ano ang allowed sa Joint Circular na expenses para sa confidential funds, maintenance, and other expenses. Kasama ba yan sa tinatawag mong exclusive listahan ng puwede paggamitan ng confidential funds, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pag sinabing maintenance and other operating expenses po, wala po siya specifically dun sa enumeration nung item 4.8.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sinabi mo, exclusive. Pag wala sa listahan, bawal. Tama, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under 4.8 po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Under 4.8 of the circular. The same observations, Mr. Witness, for the second and third quarter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang nakalagay dito ay regular funds, maintenance, and M-O-O-E. Hindi confidential funds. Based on your documents, for the second and third quarter, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents, nakalagay po MOOE. And not confidential funds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa next set of documents, Mr. Witness. Mr. Witness, want to drink water?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Okay lang po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pinom ka ng tubig. Baka pagod ko na. Pero konti na lang.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Punta naman tayo sa next set of documents. Ito naman ay Liquidation Report dated March 31, 2023, Liquidation Report dated June 30, 2023, and Liquidation Report dated September 29, 2023. Exhibits P-1-18-A, Exhibit P-1-18-B, and Exhibit P-1-18-B. dash C, respectively, common stipulated document with the defense, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the respondent? For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the respondent.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the respondent.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Respectively? Respectively, it is D-1-2-DE. Next would be D-1-26-DE. And the third one would be D-1-55-DE, Your Honor. Correct.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Counsel, please proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, please look at your document again at pakibasa yung particulars.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: first liquidation report, anong period cover dito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this liquidation report po, February 20, 2023 to March 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At anong nakalagay dito? First quarter nakalagay and it says here particulars again. Madilim. Pag-ibasa itong nakalagay under the column particulars.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under the column particulars, ang nakalagay po ay to liquidate the cash advance granted for payment of operational MOU expenses of the Vice President, Secretary of Department covered by check number 000000453 dated February 20, 2023 with DV number 2023-02-02987.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, sinabi mo M-O-O-E na naman. Maintenance and other operational expenses.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito ba ay allowed as liquidation ng confidential funds under your Joint Circular 2015?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kung M-O-O-E po yung expense, hindi po siya kasama dun sa specific enumeration ng Joint Circular under item 4.8.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kagaya ng sinabi mo, exclusive ang listahan at bawal ang wala sa listahan. Tama, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The same observation can be made. Second quarter, tama, Mr. Witness, and third quarter.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The second quarter covering what period for the record?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the second quarter, ang nakalagay po dun sa liquidation report, April to June 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And the third quarter, Mr. Witness. Ang
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: nakalagay po doon sa liquidation report, July to September 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At pareho rin nakalagay. Walang reference sa confidential funds. At sinabi mo earlier, itong MOOE, maintenance and other expenses, are dapat kasama sa regular funds, hindi confidential funds, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, Ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron dito sa bottom portion, signature.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In all three documents, there is a signature appearing
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: thereat. Pakitingin ang signature na yan.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: What particular portion po yung tinutukoy niya, Ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In the bottom portion, Mr. Witness. Flashed on the screen.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Who certified the document, Mr. Guamil?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, sinertify po ni Secretary. and Vice President Sara Duterte yung box B ng liquidation reports.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For all three quarters?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is the significance? Ano ang nakikita mong signature dito? Signature ni Vice President, tama? Sa three quarters?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on these documents. Ano naman ang significance? Ano ang importance ng nakikita natin na signature ng President, Vice President dito sa tatlong liquidation documents na pinakita mo sa court?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sinertify po ni Vice President Sara Duterte sa liquidation reports po na ito na yung purpose po nung kanilang cash advance ay na-accomplish ng agency.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang sinabi mo ay sinertify ng Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. Based on this document.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on this document, miski nakalagay sa particulars, Mr. Witness, na ang pinaggamitan ng confidential funds are maintenance and... other operational expenses, sinertify ng vice president at naginginami dito sa confidential funds. Yun ba ang ibig sabihin ng signature ng vice president, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on these documents po, yun po yung sinertify ni vice president.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We next go, we now go to the next documents, which are accomplishment reports for the three quarters.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And we will flash this on the screen showing to you these documents for your memory. Again, Your Honor, these are stipulated documents for the prosecution. This is Exhibit P-1-16A dated March 31, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Likewise, Your Honor, we are showing on the screen Another accomplishment report, which is P-1-16B, dated June 30, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And lastly, Your Honors, an accomplishment report dated September 30, 2023. Mark the exhibit P-1-16C.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And respectively, these are D-1-21DE, D-1-51DE, and D-175DE for the respondent.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: We confirm that, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Denied to the records. Counsel, you may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is the significance, Mr. Witness, of these accomplishment reports?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question, ma'am? Sorry.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the significance of the accomplishment reports, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The significance po nung accomplishment report is that dito po nakalagay yung kanilang confidential expenses na pinaggamitan nung kanilang confidential one.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And what observations do you have, if
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: any?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: On what particular period po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Per quarter. The first quarter, anong observation ang masasabi mo dito sa accomplishment report na sinubmit?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the first quarter po, meron po silang sinama na line item for confidential expenses. Hindi po among the allowable confidential expenses under item 4.8 of the Joint Circular. At yun po yung payment of incentives for traveling relative to the confidential operations under the counterinsurgency program. Also under the abuse prevention and control with schools program. Under the anti-illegal activities operations. and under the anti-extremism terrorism programs. And also, dun sa kanilang anti-extremism or terrorism programs, meron din nakalagay na provision of medical input aid which is not among the allowable expenses under item 4.8 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mga magkano, you mentioned here that the actual outcome accomplishments are purchase of information, payment of rewards, purchase of supplies, payment of incentives, traveling related to confidential information. Magkano naman ang amounts involved dito?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung payment of information. Prevention of recruitment. Ito, nakalagay dito, actual outcome. Nag-prevent daw sila ng recruitment ng mga NPA at komunista at leftist groups sa skwelahan. Magkano ang bayad daw?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the purchase of information po, 2,470,000. For the payment of reward, 2 billion pesos. For the purchase of supplies, 2,805,000 pesos. And for the payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations, 2.1 million pesos po. With a total amount po na 9,375,000 pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Para sa prevention ng recruitment ng NPA ng komunista at ng leftist sa mga eskwelahan, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under this accomplishment report, yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Nagsubmit ma ng dokumento ang DepEd kung ano-anong eskwelahan sila successful.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on their submission, wala po silang sinubmit na particular schools.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Dito rin sa column nito nakalagay, Conducted surveillance in 115 areas. May sinubmit ba ang DepEd ng listahan ng 115 areas na ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po silang sinubmit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At nakalagay dito sa item B. 100% successful daw sila. 100% implementation of activities without untoward security-related incidents. Itong activities na to, na 100% compliance daw. Meron bang listahan na sinubmit ang DepEd para dito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Last column, reduce abuses against learners.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: purchase of information, payment of reward, purchase of supplies, payment of incentives, or traveling. Pakibasa, Mr. Witness, magkano ang total na
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: binayad allegedly ng DepEd para daw ma-reduce ang abuso sa mga studyante?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this accomplishment report, 10 million pesos po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I'm sorry. What else did you observe, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this accomplishment report, meron din po silang payment of reward na 2 million pesos for the counterinsurgency programs, 2,130,000 pesos for the abuse prevention and control within schools,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 1.5 million pesos for the anti-illegal activities operations, 1,879,000 pesos for the anti-extremism terrorism programs. Pero wala po silang sinamit na document. Evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Base sa observation mo at sa mga sinabi mo dito, meron bang violations ito ng Joint Circular 2015?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, na-violate po yung item 4.8.5 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pakiulit nga kung ano yung item 4.8.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung item 4.8.5 po, dun nakalagay yung three conditions for a valid payment of reward. Una, it must be approved by the head of the agency. Pangalawa, it must be supported with a document evidencing the success of the information gathering or surveillance activity on the account of the information given by the informer. At pangatlo, ay dapat directly related yung activity to the conduct of the confidential activities of the agency concerned.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman? Mr. Witness, para sa unang item, prevention of recruitment, etc., 9.3 million. Para sa reduction of abuse against learners, 10 million. Para sa eliminate illegal activities sa loob ng skwelahan,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: another 9 million. At para kumuha ng alleged mga information.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: para i-implement daw itong mga programs na to, 9.1. At lahat-lahat, iba-iba. Pero ang total na naman ito, basahin mo nga ang total for the period February 20, March 30, 2023.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang total po ay 37.5 million pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Eksakto, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Eksakto po sa cash advance nila.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Eksakto sa cash advance nila.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa last page dito, and I'll show you now the last page, there is here,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: approved by. Anong ibig sabihin?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang ibig sabihin po ng approved by ay in-approve po nung signatory kung ano man yung contents ng accomplishment report.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At tela, sino ang signatory nito ng accomplishment report na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang signatory po ay si Vice President and Education Secretary, Sara Duterte po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We now go to the next document. Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: if I'm not mistaken, that's the second to the last document, correct?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The certification and then the AOM.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Just so that we can pause for lunch after those two documents so that we don't cut you off in regard to your direct. I presume you will be ending your direct after those two documents are identified by the witness? Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor. If I may, just for... for expediency sake, only, of course, if the distinguished opposing counsel would allow. Since these documents are quite similar except for the amounts, we are willing to stipulate that the witness will have the same observations for the second quarter, the third quarter, ang pagkakaiba lang po siguro ay yung amounts.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With respect, you're referring to the certification?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Sorry, the accomplishment reports. I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: think, so stipulated, no need to proceed with respect to the other two documents. Same observation except for the amounts.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, without accepting, of course, the interpretation of the witness which goes without
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: saying. Of course. But same testimony with respect to his observation for the second and the third quarter that he gave in regard to the first quarter. If that is okay with the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: opposing, distinguished opposing counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor, it is in order and with our counter-manifestation that the testimony of this witness by way of explanation to these accomplishment reports for the second and third quarter be likewise adopted by way of reference and explanation to why these activities are in violation of the Joint Circular 2015, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Same testimony with respect to the first quarter. Julie noted, counsel may proceed with certifications and I guess the AUM. Again, before we pause for lunch, counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: now go to three certifications. And this is a DepEd certification dated March 31, 2023. DepEd certification dated June 30, 2023. And DepEd certification dated October 2, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: P-1-15-B and P-1-15-C. And
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: likewise for the respondent, D-1-6-DE, D-1-30-DE and D-1-59-DE. We
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: confirm, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Counselor, proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, it is now our turn to ask if counsel is willing to stipulate as to these DepEd certifications as to the meaning of a test. and as to the signature in these documents being the signature of the Vice President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And that these are pro forma documents or the witness previously did not see anything, did not observe anything extraordinary.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes. Counter-manifestation that these are templates and that we do not admit the interpretation of what attest means but we do accept that the witness will have the same explanation, his explanation of what attest means.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: In regard to it being pro forma. Yes.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: If I may, that pro forma to me means copy-paste, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Which I objected to. I hope you understand.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Akala ko makakalusot. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Stipulation duly noted by both parties.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Lastly, Mr. Witness, after auditing all of these documents you identified and giving your explanations as to why, based on these documents, your evaluation thereat, you stated that they are non-compliant or violation or bawal or irregular compared based on the Joint Circular 2015. What did you do?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: The statement was a conclusion, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The witness earlier stated that he observed certain non-compliant entries in the submissions from the office of the Vice President.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: We submit, Your Honor. We're
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: going to the AOM already, counsel. Please proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Having observed what you earlier testified to, discrepancies, irregularities, pagkukulang, mga bawal na submissions, Ano ang ginawa mo after making this evaluation?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I drafted po an audit observation memorandum containing po yung findings noted during the audit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you drafted this? Anong nangyari sa draft mo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung 41st and 2nd quarter po ay na-issue po dun sa OVP, ay dun sa DPED po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, I'm now showing to you a certified true copy. Assisting
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsels may approach.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: audit, observation, memorandum dated February 1, 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Being flashed on the screen as well.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mark, Your Honor, as prosecutions exhibit P-1-21A, common exhibit with the defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the defense, it's D-1-132, correct, counsel?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: No, Your Honors, it's D-1-111-DE. 111.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Noted. And Mr. Witness, look at your document to refresh your memory. What periods does this Audit Information Memorandum cover?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this Audit Observation Memorandum, ang period covered po ay March 20, April 20 to March 30, 2023 at April 20 to June 29, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And Mr. Witness, please tell us what your recommendations are. or were, if any.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: May recommendations po include, first, yung hindi po na-submit ni DepEd yung kanilang documentary evidence of payments for their confidential expenses.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano po, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa accomplishment report po nila, meron pong line items na hindi allowable under the item 4.8 of the Joint Circular at yun po yung Provision of medical input, aid at payment of incentives or traveling relative to the confidential operations of the DepEd.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What else, Mr. Witness? And for the appreciation of the Honorable Impeachment Court, this is being flashed on the screen and boxed in red. What else, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung payment of rewards po nila ay hindi supported ng documents evidencing the success of the information gathering and or surveillance activities on account of the information given by the informer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Anything else, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Number 4 po, yung kanilang physical and financial plan hindi po naka-indicate yung specific confidential activities na pagbabasayan ng kanilang disbursement in violation of the item 4.2 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung kanilang disbursement voucher po ay in-approve ni Undersecretary Annalyn M. Sevilla instead of the head of the agency in violation of item 6.3.1b of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And who is this person that you mentioned?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the document submitted, si Annalyn M. Sevilla po yung Undersecretary for Finance ng DepEd
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: during
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: the time po na na-issue tong AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And the signature?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can you identify the signature?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Signature po, sa'ng part po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: On the last page of this document.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Which among these po?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The AOM, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Which among these signatures po yung tinutukoy niyo? There
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is a signature here above the name Assistant Commissioner Officer in Charge, Nilda B. Laras. Can you identify this signature?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And why?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kasi nakita ko po siyang pumirma ng ibang documents at yung signature niya on those documents is the same po with this one.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: There are signatures as well below.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: It says, proof of receipt of AOM, Vice President Sara Z. Duterte, Vice President Edward Fajarda, SDO, the Chief Accountant, the COA ATL DepEd. You confirm? These names and their designations?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat po, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In the proof of receipt of this AOM, meron mga nakalagay na pangalan na received daw ng Sara Z. Duterte. Pero hindi niya signature to. Merong Gloria Mendoza. Edward Fajarda, the SDO. What does SDO mean, Mr. Witness? The
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Special
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Dispersing Officer po, based on the Rejoined Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Also received by his office, and likewise, the COA, Chief Accountant, and the COA ATL, received this AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mr. Witness, you confirm that?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nareceive po siya ng mga nakapirma po dito sa signature part po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What happened next, if any, if you know?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala na po akong personal knowledge since before po sila magbigay ng response, na-transfer na po ako out of ICFAO to another audit sector of COA.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And you got transferred when?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: On February 12 po of 2024.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, Mr. Witness, and this is the second to the last question, Mr. Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Could you tell us, after you did this audit evaluation and these recommendations, what happened next? What other matters occurred, if any, in connection with your audit?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: From when po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: During the time that you were still there.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: There was a time po that I was called in a meeting.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Tinawag ka sa meeting.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At nandun ka pa sa COA-ICFA.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Maalala mo anong date itong meeting na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: It was around second week po nung September of 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sino-sino ang nasa meeting na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang naalala ko po ay si Atty. Zuleika Lopez at si Atty. Michael Powa po. At yung dating head po ng ICFAO na si Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras at si Atty. Gloria Camora po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sinong nagtawag ng meeting na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi ko na po ma-recall kung sino nagtawag. Ang naalala ko lang po ay pinasama po ako dun sa meeting na yun.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pinasama ka? Bakit ka pinasama sa meeting na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Dahil ako po yung in-charge of the audit of the confidential fund nung DepEd at OVP po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kilala mo ba, Mr. Witness, si Atty. Michael Poa?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nakikita ko po siya sa news.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakikita mo siya sa news? Hindi mo siya nakikita sa in-person? Kaya no?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: During that time, sorry, hindi po clear yung particular period.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kilala mo ba? When you went to that meeting, were you able to identify Attorney Michael Powa?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nagpakilala po sila, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nagpakilala sa'yo. Okay. And what happened during that meeting? Attorney, sorry for that.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: No, no, no, that's fine.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nagpapagising lang tayo. You confirmed that this is the attorney that you saw in that meeting?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. What happened sa meeting na yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: They asked po about the liquidation process po ng confidential fund and yung mga supporting documents po na required with respect to the liquidation documents po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Sinabi mo, before I go to the next question, sinabi mo na nandun lens si... Atty.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Zuleika Lopez.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa pagkakalala ko po, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Do
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you know? Did you know then who she was?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nagpakilala po siya sa amin as the Chief of Staff of the OB People.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Chief of Staff of?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: The Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ano naman ang connection niya, if at all, sa DepEd?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po siyang sinabing na connection niya with the DepEd. Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon naman, Mr. Witness, tell us what transpired, if you recall, of that meeting sometime in September.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: They asked po about the liquidation process po nung cash advances as well as kung ano po yung mga supporting documents required.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And anong sagot? Tinanong nila, again, tinanong nila kung anong mga requirements.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: nila alam ang mga requirements para sa...
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: They clarified po kasi may mga agencies din po na nagka-clarify sa amin about requirements ng Joint Circular since it is very technical po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ano naman ang sagot ninyo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: They were referred po by Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras to the Joint Circular for the specific requirements.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And nung sinabi ni... ng COA IGFAO, sinabi ni Assistant Commissioner Nilda Plaras ang requirements. Ano ang reaction nila? Ni Atty. Zuleika at ni Atty. POA. Kung maalala mo.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nag-confirm naman kanyang reaction po ni Atty. Zuleika.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi mo, during the meeting, Mr. Witness, tinanong nila ano ang mga requirements.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: para mag-submit ng documents para liquidation ng confidential funds. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sinabi naman, ang sagot eh...
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: They were referred to the Joint Circular. Joint Circular. And sinabi din po ni Associate Commissioner Nilda Paraclaras na in case merong makitang findings during the audit, ay mag-i-issue po ng AOM.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Noong sinabi ng...
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Assistant Commissioner. Eh, basahin nyo na lang yung Joint Circular. Ano naman ang response nila?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Well, they ask po if instead of an audit observation memorandum in case may audit findings, ay audit query na lang po yung i-issue sa kanila.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Audit query na lang ang dapat i-issue? Yun ba ang sinabi nila? Ano naman itong audit query na sinabi nila, ito na lang please ang i-issue ninyo, huwag na lang AOM? Ano? What is an audit query, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po ako familiar sa audit query since hindi naman po siya kasama dun sa issue 1 under the Joint Circular 2015-01.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa Joint Circular, walang audit query?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, anong nangyari nung sinabi nilang audit query na lang, please, ang i-issue ninyo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: po. Bakit?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Anong
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: nangyari?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po pumayag si ICFAO since hindi naman po sa sanction nung aming Joint Circular 2015-01. So nag-issue pa rin po kami ng AOM nung may nanote po kaming findings during the audit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. So nag-issue pa rin despite this meeting ng isang AOM. Pagkatapos nun, anong nangyari if you still recall?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: After po ma-approve yung AOM, nag-attempt po kaming iserve. yung AOM to the office address po nung OBP, pero hindi po siya tinanggap dahil wala lang po mag-receive na authorized person.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. And, itong first attempt n'yo, pagkatapos nun, anong nangyari?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: On the afternoon of the same date po na nag-attempt kami to serve, nagbigay po sila ng revised accomplishment report sa ICFAO.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ngayon, Mr. Witness,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sinabi mo,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: kahapon at ngayon na ang basis ng inyong post-audit or compliance audit ay ang Joint Circular.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 2015
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ng limang government agencies. Kasama dyan ang COA. Tama.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: If
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I show you at babasahin ko, flash on the screen, Section 1 of the Joint Circular. Can we please flash it on the screen?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ini-explain dito and please refer. Do you have a copy with you?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po. I have a copy po with me.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I refer you now to
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the last sentence which says,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The COA shall promulgate accounting and auditing rules and regulations, including those for the prevention of irregular, unnecessary, excessive, extravagant, or unconscionable expenditures or uses of government funds and property. You confirm, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I'm based on this joint circular, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. So, if
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: I ask you,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: sa mga sinubmit na documents ng Vice President, and I will, for purposes of summarizing, Purchase of information, 14 million.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Reward payment, 10,050,000. Rental of safe house, 11 days, nag-rent ang Office of the Vice President ng safe houses from December 21 to 31, 16 million in 11 days. divided by the number of days, 2 million a day ang binayad ng Office of the Vice President para lang sa rental ng safe house. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: May I refer po to the document po?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Refer to the document. It's in front of you. Meron pa rin mga ibang expenses.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron nakalagay
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa summary, payment of reward, various, 34,857,000.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron din. Purchase supplies, 11,813,000. Payment of rewards, Mr. Witness, 24 million, 10 million. Payment of rewards, rewards in medicine, in kind. 24,930,000, Mr. Witness. Payment of rental of transport vehicles related, allegedly, to confidential activities, 10 million pesos. Tables and chairs, 500,000 pesos. Desktop computers and printers, 3 million pesos. pesos.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You confirm that, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pwede pong paulit ng enumeration kasi I don't
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: have preference. Ito ay nasa notice of
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: suspension
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and your tabulation.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Okay, ma'am.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Do you confirm, Mr. Wamil?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Yes, Your Honor, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Based on Section 1 of
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the Joint Circular. I-translate ko na lang. Anong ibig sabihin n'yo?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Irregular. I'm sorry. This is my last question.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Medyo limited ang aking Tagalog o Pilipino. Ang pagkaintindi ko sa irregular e kaduda-duda. Tama? Kaduda-duda. Irregular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang counsel for respondent, if you can help me, it's in this translation. Happily welcome your translation. Unnecessary sa Pilipino. Unnecessary, hindi kailangan.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Irregular is hindi palagi, hindi kinagawian.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi pangkaraniwan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Irregular. Counsel, correspondent,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: do you agree? Hindi pangkaraniwan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Your Honor, I do.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kasi ang nalaman lang natin the other day is unusual. Ngayon naman, irregular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi pangkaraniwan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi pangkaraniwan. Unnecessary. Hindi kailangan.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, I would all do respect again if you may just ask the question na lang po. Sandali.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Preliminary, Your Honor. Preliminary. Because this
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is already, I
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: think we all
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: know what's happening here.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In any event, Your Honor, give me some leeway here. This is the last question before we break up for lunch and considering the
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: victory
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: of Ayala, Your Honor. We're all in a happy mood.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let council wind up with our direct council correspondent. Let's give her some leeway. Let's help in translating more accurately.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Unnecessary, hindi kailangan.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Excessive, labis, labis.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Extravagan,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Maluho.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: E ang nakalagay dito, bongga kaday.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ekstravagant. Bongga. Ekstravagant. At lastly, unconscionable. Sabi ng Atty. Virgil, kasuklam-suklam. Unconscionable. Okay, Mr. Witness, sa binasa natin, Section 1, saan, if at all, itong mga binasa ko,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: saan babagsak?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Objection, Your Honor. Question calls for a conclusion.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: relation to his observation only, not as to the conclusion of law, given that the AUM is not a final disposition of
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the matter at hand. In relation to your observation and based on the audited documents, will
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: it fall, if any, under any of this enumeration?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am. Under the irregular expenditures.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Irregular.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Irregular po siya dahil hindi po siya compliant or hindi po siya compliant with the provisions of the Joint Circular 2015-01 which is an issuance po of the COA, the DBM, the DILG, the GOCC, GCG, and the Department of National Education, National Defense rather.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay, and my last question to you, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Let us go now to paragraph 8.3. of the Joint Circular. And this is being flashed on the screen for the record and for better appreciation of this honorable court. Please read paragraph 8.3.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under item 8.3, failure of the accountable officer to liquidate any public funds for which he is accountable upon demand by any duly authorized officer shall be prima facie evidence that he has put such missing funds or property to personal use and benefit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So nakalagay dito sa 8.3, you are a lawyer as well, Mr. Witness, apart from an auditor. Ano ang ibig sabihin dito ng prima facie evidence?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang ibig sabihin po ng prima facie evidence under 8.3 ay nagkaroon po ng presumasyon na ginamit yung funds for the personal use and benefit of the accountable officers.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So kung ang accountable officer at masasabi mo ba ng Vice President and concurrently Secretary of Education, masasabi mo ba na accountable officer ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the Joint Circular po, yes po, kasi under the Joint Circular, it shall be the responsibilities of the head of agency to oversee the agency-wide use of the confidential fund and to ensure compliance with the requirements of the Joint Circular. And also, in attest po ni Vice President, in her capacity as the Vice President of the Philippines and the Secretary of the DepEd, yung certification ng accountable officers na ginamit yung Pond of Order confidential expenses.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ngayon, ang confidential fund, sa binasa mo, ang confidential fund ba ay public fund?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung post-audit mo naman na sinabi mo ay Irregular. May discrepancies. Ito ba ang inaudit mo ay liquidation documents ng Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 44th quarter of 2022 until 3rd quarter of 2023 po. Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sinabi mo based on 8.3 na merong funds na hindi ma-account o walang dokumento na sinamit ang Vice President. Tama. At ang DepEd. Tama.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pwedeng paulit po ng question.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sinabi mo yesterday at ngayong araw na merong mga pondo na hindi naman confidential funds, ginamit sa confidential funds. Or sinabing ginamit sa confidential funds pero wala naman dokumento. Objection,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor. Misleading as to dun sa sinabi na wala naman.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sustained, counsel. Kindly reform.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. So you said here, that if an accountable officer, pag hindi na-explain ng isang accountable officer ang paggamit ng public funds, kagaya ng confidential funds, meron tinatawag na prima facie evidence. Anong tawag doon? Presumption?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Presumption.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Presumption ng ano?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under 8.3 po, presumption na yung fund po ay na-convert into personal use or benefit.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: presumption na na-convert for personal use or benefit, applicable dito sa sinabi mo.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Conclusion of law, Your Honor. Calls for a conclusion.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, that is... Your Honor,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: all these matters are pending still. Sustained.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please. Ang tawag ko nang doon. hindi prima facie evidence. Kung akong tatanungin, scam ito.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Move to strike, Your Honor. Move to strike. That is out of order, Your Honor. No
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: further questions, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Move
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to strike.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So stricken from the record, no further questions. Direct examination is completed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent, Tony Poa, we shall have your cross after we resume for a brief lunch break. We shall resume at 1.15. for our lunch break.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Trial is in recess.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hereby resumed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mr. Wamil, we shall continue with your testimony and you shall be testifying under the same oath. You understand, sir?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly respond through the mic.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Okay, po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We shall now proceed with the cross-examination of the counsel for respondent. Atty. Powa, you may proceed when you're ready.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor. Thank you.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Mr. Wamil, good afternoon, po, sir.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Good afternoon, po, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Sa pagkaalala ko po, nabanggit niya po, that you were formerly with ICFAO as a state auditor. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And you are a certified public accountant. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: You're also a lawyer, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: You passed the bar in 2022?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: 2023 po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ah, 2023. Okay, I stand corrected. And Mr. Wamil, you also testified yesterday during your direct examination that you were part of the team. that audited the OBP and DepEd confidential funds. Is that correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po, Tim, kasi ako lang po yung nag-evaluate ng documents.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ah, ikaw mismo, basically, nag-evaluate ng documents. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay, just so maintindihan lang namin how ICPAU conducts its audit. Yung mga auditors po ba, do they go to the field and observe itong mga confidential operations in person?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Since what we do po is compliance audit, we base our audit on the documents being submitted to the ICFAO.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And do you get special training as auditors pagdating sa how confidential or intelligence operations are conducted?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: We
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: base po our observations on the provisions naman po ng Joint Circular 2015-01.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Basically, what you're saying is you base your audit on the documents submitted to you, not just by DepEd or OVP, but by any other government agency. Ganyan sa ICPAU.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents if they are compliant with the requirements of the Joint Circular 2015-01. Correct. Thank you. So,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: pagdating po dun sa mga dokumento na tatanggap n'yo from OVP and DepEd, binabasa n'yo po ito isa-isa, no? Lahat ng attachments?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po ako yung nag-receive
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: noon. Meron po kaming receiving staff po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Pero kayo po, in your evaluation, do you go through the documents one by one?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po. I evaluate po if they are compliant with the requirements of the Joint Circular. Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, when you evaluated these documents, nakita niyo po ba doon kung sino ang nag-approve ng grant ng confidential funds for OVP for the fourth quarter of 2022?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nakita ko po doon
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: sa distribution voucher po. na si Asek, Linuel G. Ortonio po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: No, I mean the grant. Kasi wala po sa gaah yung OVP Confidential Funds for 2022 eh. So nakita niyo po ba kung sino ang nag-approve nung grant para sa fourth quarter 2022 Confidential Funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents submitted, si Office of the President po yung nag-approve. That's correct. Opo, Office of the President.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Pagdating naman po sa OVP 2023 Confidential Funds, Yun po ay nasa General Appropriations Act. Do you confirm that? Yes po. And pagdating naman po sa DepEd, 2023 Confidential Funds, nasa General Appropriations Act din po. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And as a lawyer, you would know that the GAA is enacted by Congress. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: That's correct.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now yesterday, naalala ko po, natanong kayo, doon sa time nyo sa ICFAO, kung ilang vice president ang na-audit n'yo pagdating sa confidential funds. Alala n'yo po yun? Yes po, sir. At ang sagot n'yo po ay isa lang si vice president Sara Duterte, the respondent in this case. Tama po ba? Yes po. Since
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I assumed in ICPAO in 2014.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Since you assumed in September 2014?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po. And you were asked bakit si vice president lang? Naalala nyo yung tanong na yun?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At ang sagot nyo po kasi since you assume siya lang po ang vice president na nagkaroon ng appropriations for confidential funds. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po. Since September 2014 po lang nag-assume ako. Apo.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now I'm showing you a document. If I may approach the witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may approach.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I am showing you a document entitled... I am
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: showing
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: you a document and this document is from the Department of Budget and Management entitled Special Allotment Release Order Dated. Medyo malabo lang po yung document. December 22, 2014.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Nakita niyo po yan.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: At ang purpose po... is to cover confidential activities for fiscal year 2014.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Do you see that? Yes, sir. And noong December 22, 2014, nasa ICFAO na po kayo. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Anong period po yan, sir?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: We have a clear here po. Date of issue, December 22, 2014.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, nasa ICFAO na po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: At
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: hindi po si Vice President Sara Duterte ang Vice President ng mga panahon na yun. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Pero na-liquidate po ba yan? That's the question. That's the question to IGPOW actually because yun po yung ang pinapakita ko lang sa inyo is nagkaroon po ng confidential funds. Ang Office of the Vice President noong 2014 issued. December 22, 2014.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on that document po. Meron. You
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: confirm. But that's okay, no? Because maybe you were just not aware yesterday when you were asked the question. I just wanted to put that on record because marami na rin pong lumalabas sa social media na si Vice President Sara Duterte lang ang Vice President na nagkaroon ng
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: confidential funds. But you confirmed that, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honors, just a manifestation, this has not been pre-marked. We just came upon this document yesterday after the statements were made. So upon the agreement made during pre-trial, We request that this be marked as exhibit for the defense D-1-167-DE, sorry, dash OVP. Let it be so, Mark. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Provisional only, Your Honor.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, of course, subject to the objections of the prosecution when the time is appropriate.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Of course, at the proper time.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor. And we will provide the prosecution with a copy as well.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: kindly
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: do
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: that after, perhaps later on, after the trial, or now too, so that it can be made a subject matter of redirect to the counsel for the panel of prosecutors. I can give you
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: just a
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: photo. We would like to manifest that this is just a printout, Your Honor, and a photocopy that we retrieved from the office of the Vice President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ito,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: bibigyan ba natin ito?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Anyway, Mr. Witness, nung pinag
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: -aaralan ko yung nature ng confidential funds, may mga issuances akong nakita aside from yung JC 2015-01 na parating yung namimention kahapon and today. And that is COA Circular 92-985. Yun po ba ay familiar sa inyo?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I can give you a copy. Your Honor, I am giving the witness a copy of a document entitled Commission and Audit, Circular No. 92-385, dated October 21, 1992. For the reference of the court, this was marked as Exhibit D-1-155.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Naalala po ba ninyo yung document na yan or familiar po ba kayo sa document na yan?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Witnesses perusing the document, Your Honors?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: If Assistant Counsel would like to also from the prosecution?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness will please answer.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Are you familiar with that
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: document?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I am not familiar po with that document. Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That's okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Meron lang po ditong whereas clauses. I won't ask you about the entire document anyway. Meron lang po ditong whereas clauses on the first page. Can you see that? Mr. Witness?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Whereas
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: clauses.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I would just want you to read the fourth whereas clause.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ito pa. Ma'am, you want to come here so you'd have a better view. Just the fourth whereas clause. Can you please read that out loud for the record?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Kapunan, it's also flashed on the screen.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Whereas, these intelligence and confidential activities by their very nature are highly sensitive and confidential operations or missions, details of which cannot be divulged without posing a threat to national security or to the success of the mission. Can
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: you please read the next whereas as well? Thank you.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: As now being required, the submission of receipts, bills or commercial invoices in support of disbursements from this fund or rental of safe houses, purchase of meals or supplies, and other expenses may create a leak of information that may threaten the confidentiality of the intelligence operations, endanger the lives and the safety of the agents and employees of the government agencies, and result to a failure of the mission.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And just the next two whereas clauses na lang po para hindi na po tayo humaba.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Whereas in many instances, it is impractical and sometimes impossible to obtain such receipts, bills, or commercial invoices during intelligence operations. Whereas by its very nature, the use of intelligence and or confidential plans requires an approach allowing more flexibility in intelligence operations.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: In manifestation, Your Honor, first of all, this exhibit presented by counsel for the respondent. is dated October 1, 1992, Your Honor, whereas the joint circular cited as basis by this witness, Your Honor, is dated 2015, Your Honor. There is no indication here. Okay. There is an indication here, Your Honor, that all issuances in consistency with are hereby... amended or revoked accordingly. Similar provision, Your Honor, by way of manifestation,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: is
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: likewise in, is likewise, Your Honor, mentioned in the Joint Circular 2015, observation for the record that 2015 supersedes this circular cited by counsel for respondent which is dated 1992, Your Honor, for the record.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor. But again, we'd like just a counter-manifestation that the repealing clause under JC 2015-01 states, and I quote, all circulars, memoranda, rules, regulations, and other issuance inconsistent herewith are deemed repealed and superseded accordingly.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So the repealing clause in 201.5-1 did not specify COA circular 92-8985. Precisely our point, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please counter manifestation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Of course, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Counsel read the literal meaning, Your Honor, but the substantive meaning is all circulars, all circulars are deemed repealed and superseded accordingly. His interpretation, my interpretation, but no interpretation needed, Your Honor. 9.0 is expressed, all. are repealed and superseded accordingly.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Manifestation as Duly noted. Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor, the documents would speak for themselves and we will leave this to the Honorable Court as to not prolong the debate on this matter.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Just again, just my last manifestation on this. The difference between Joint Circular 2015, Your Honor, it has been
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: identified, authenticated, and testified to by this witness. This circular that they are citing, Your Honor, 1992, has not been identified. We don't know its due existence. We don't know the circumstances surrounding this document. And therefore, they're covered by the original document rule. Produce the original, since you don't have a witness who has testified. as to its existence, due execution, and least of all, its content, Your Honor. And we are stating that this should be clearly in the records of this proceeding, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted without prejudice to respondent presenting during their evidence-in-chief the original copy of the document and someone testifying thereto. We submit, Your Honor. Please proceed, counsel.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Doon, base po sa binasa n'yo, Mr. Witness, nakikita natin na mag-iba ang auditing standards or guidelines pagdating sa confidential or intelligence funds kung ikukumpara sa regular funds. Tama po yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Well, based on the Joint Circular 2015-01, magkaiba po yung treatment between confidential funds and intelligence funds.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Opo. At base rin po doon, sa binasa n'yo, Ang kadalasan nangyayari pag resibo o invoices ay maaaring maging impraktikal kung yun ang ire-require. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under the joint circular po kasi, the auditors may require the... Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor, that's not responsive. I was just asking him to confirm what he read.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly answer the question, witness.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Just on the circular that you read. Circular 92-3. Can you repeat the question,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: sir?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ayon po doon. Yung regular requirement na paghihingi ng mga resibo, acknowledgement receipts, may be impractical pagdating po sa confidential operation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Can we ask counsel, Your Honor, to show that particular position that he is citing in respect of the circular?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Can we do so, counsel?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Tama po ba? Ang sabi po dito ay during intelligence operations. Yes. Tama po ba? As stated po dito, during intelligence operations. Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you. Well, I'll accept that answer, Your Honor.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, punta naman po tayo doon sa nature ng confidential operations. You would agree with me na pagdating po sa confidential operations, delikado po pag nagkakaroon ng leak of information. Tama po ba?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Delikado po kung magkaroon ng leak ng mga information na nakukuha patay sa isang confidential operation.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I think
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the witness would have been able to answer. Witness may answer?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, [unclear] the classified nature of the confidential fund.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: thank you, Mr. Witness. In fact, you being a lawyer, you know that there are laws prohibiting the unauthorized disclosure of confidential information, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: You being
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: a lawyer, sir, you are aware that there are laws prohibiting the unauthorized disclosure of confidential information, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you state what the specific laws po yung...
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Revised Penal Code under Article 229, for example, under Revelation of Secrets.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, Republic Act 3019, Section 3, Paragraph K, on unauthorized divulging of confidential information, correct?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: and you being a public officer under 6713, alam nyo rin po na hindi po pwedeng basta-basta mag-disclose without the authority ng mga confidential information. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. So, batay po dito, pinapahalagan po talaga ang confidentiality pagdating sa mga classified information na ito. Tama po ba? You would agree with me?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes. Now, let's go to the Joint Circular that we have been mentioning since yesterday. Ito pong Joint Circular No. 2015-01. And I'm referring to the circular with which we have pre-marked as D-1-136 for the defense, Your Honors. And I think we will be flashing that on the screen as well.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ito naman po yung pag-usapan natin. I just wanted you, Mr. Witness, to give us the definition of confidential funds. Diyan po sa circular na yan under, I think it's page 2, item 3.7. Can you please read it for the record?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under 3.7, confidential fund refers to the lump sum amount provided as such in the GAA for NGAs. in appropriation ordinances for LGUs and in the COBs for GOCCs for their confidential expenses.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Salamat po, Mr. Witness. At pagdating po, nabasa nyo po yung word na lump sum. Ibig po sabihin ito, buong halaga, buong
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: amount, as opposed to having line items for expense. Tama po ba?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Lump sum. Lump sum.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Opo.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At based on your experience, pag ang pinag-uusapan po natin ay confidential funds, Pagdating po sa pag-dispers nito, cash po ba ito? In the form of cash?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: What expense
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: are you
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: paying? Confidential funds in general. Cash po ba ito?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala pong specific provision kung anong type po yung ibabayad.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. But item 6 provides for the guidelines on cash advances, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document po, yes po. Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And I refer you now to item 6.1.2.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Diyan po, sinasabi po ng provision na yan na ang maari lang mag-avail ng cash advance pagdating sa confidential funds ay ang isang designated bonded special disbursing officer or SDO or kung wala mang ganong designated SDO ay ang head of agency, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At kanina po, sabi nyo, binasa nyo bawat pahina noong mga sinabite sa inyo ng DepEd at OVP for their liquidation reports. Tama po ba?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At you would be aware na ang STO po para po sa OVP ay si Ms. Gina Acosta. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents submitted, yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, thank you. At pagdating naman po sa DepEd, Mr. Witness, ang STO po ay si Mr. Edward Fajarda. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents submitted po, yes po.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So based on that, Tama rin po ba na sila ang maging payees ng mga cheque na inilabas ng DepEd para sa cash advance?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po. At tama rin po na silang nag-encash ng mga cheque dahil silang payee.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So they complied with 6.1.2, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: What do you mean complied po?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Complied with the requirements of 6.1.2 na ang SDO po ang kumuha ng cash advance at siya po nag-encash ng cheque.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please misleading. That's not the only requirement in 6.1.1. 6.1.2, Your Honor. There are other requirements here. Can counsel be specific? I'm
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: just
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: asking, Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is a blanket he is saying, and so therefore, there is compliance here. In particular.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you. I appreciate po the... What does counsel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for respondent say?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I appreciate naman po the objection of the good counsel. So I will be more specific. Tama po. Nag-comply po ng SDO ang payee sa cheque at ang SDO pong nag-encash. Yun lang po. Just on that part.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents, si SDO yung payee ng cheque and yung nag-encash nung cheque. Okay. Thank
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: you po. Now, I'll refer you to item 6.1.5 of the Joint Circular. Can you please read just the first sentence of that provision?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Cash advances shall be limited to the requirements for three months. Thank
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: you, Mr. Witness. So tama po ba ang pagkakaintindi ko na para sa cash advance at any one time, ang maximum na pwede mo lang ma-cash advance ay yung requirements mo para sa tatlong buwan ng confidential operations?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: on
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: this
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: provision po, yes.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At tatlong buwan po is equivalent to one quarter of a year, tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Now, base po dyan sa provision na yan, nakasulat na ang maximum amount ay para sa tatlong buwan. Pero meron po bang provision dyan na nagbabawal na gamitin ito in perhaps 60 days?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Meron po bang nagbabawal na gamitin ito in 11
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: days?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala din po. Kaya hindi po namin sinama sa findings namin yung 11 days na disbursement. It's just a statement of fact po on the AOM.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: you for confirming that, Mr. Witness. Familiar po kayo bilang isang CPA sa accrual method of accounting?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Can you just, in simple terms, because I'm not even a CPA, just
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: give us a glimpse kung ano ibig sabihin. Ano ba ang accrual
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: method of accounting?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kapag sinabing accrual method of accounting, yung expenses ay nirecord upon incurrence, not upon payment.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Opo, okay. So, dito po ba, pwede po ba yung parang I'm just a simple-minded person? Parang buy now, pay later? Ganon?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala po yan sa joint circular so I am not authorized to answer
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: that question. I will leave it at that. Punta na lang po tayo sa liquidation. Sa liquidation po, under the joint circular, that's under 6.2.2, correct? Under 6.2.2, if I may just refer you to that provision, dapat po maliquidate o magsumite ng liquidation report ang isang agency na may confidential intelligence funds within 30 days after the close of a quarter.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Tatlo po yung nakalagay dito, hindi lang po the... 30 days after every quarter.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Sige po, please enumerate for us.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under 6.2.2 of the Joint Circular, all cash advances for CF and IF shall be liquidated within 30 days after every quarter or from the approved target date of completion of the project or activity or after the cash advance had been fully utilized, whichever comes first in accordance with the procedures as stated. Okay, thank you po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ngayon po, papakita ko po sa inyo yung liquidation report na isinumite ng OVP for their fourth quarter confidential funds 2022. Maybe this time we could just ask our assisting counsel, Your Honor, to hand the document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Assisting counsel for the other side may
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: also approach.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Maaari niyo po bang matukoy kung anong date po na-receive ng Kuwa Ikfaw itong liquidation report ng OVP?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the transmitted letter, January 17, 2023.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For our understanding, what exhibit number?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ah, sorry. Thank you for reminding me, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You're welcome.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: This is Exhibit D-1-4-OVP.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is the prosecution's P-1-11-A. Ah, no, I'm sorry.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I'm sorry, what is it? D-1.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Sorry. D-1-1. Sorry, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I was just corrected.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: For the record, this is not a common exhibit.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Duly noted.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, base po sa date na nabasa n'yo, compliant po ba na within the 30-day period ay nakapagsumite sila? Yung act lang po ng pag-submission, na pag-submit rather, ng liquidation report.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this document, yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes po. And kung mapapansin nyo po, dun po sa transmittal, meron pong isang checklist. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And I will refer you now to item 6.2.2.3 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ayon po sa 6.2.3 ng nasabing Joint Circular 2015-01, ang gagawin po ng receiving officer ng COA-ICFAO, ay titignan po yung checklist, tapos susuriin po yung mga dokumentong isinumintay ng ahensya, yung mga attachments, kung pasok siya doon sa checklist of supporting documents na kinakailangan. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat your question po?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ayon po, sa 6.2.2.3, ang receiving officer ng Kuwa Ikfaw ay titignan yung checklist And then, titignan din, susuriin yung mga naka-attached na dokumento kung compliance siya dun sa checklist. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, based on the joint circular.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Based on that same provision, kung yun po ay kompleto, tatanggapin po ng Kuwa Ikfaw. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At pag hindi po kompleto o meaning kulang po yung mga attached documents, yun po ay dapat ibalik ng Kuwa Ikfaw sa ahensya at hindi muna tatanggapin. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po. Based on this provision po.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Apo.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And in this case, because of the receiving stamp, would you say na tinanggap po ng ikfaw ang submission ng OBP?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: As stamp po nung ikfaw, yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Thank you, Mr. Witness. Now, basing on this document na natanggap ng Kuwa Ikfaw noong January 17, 2023, ang kanilang liquidation report, meaning kanila, meaning the OVP for the fourth quarter 2022 confidential funds. It took more or less eight months for COA to issue its official finding. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I am showing you a copy of the AOMs that you issued that were also presented yesterday.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: May we know the exhibit numbers, Your Honor?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes, Your Honor. I will get to that.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Are
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you showing the one for the OVP or the DepEd? OVP, Your Honor. OVP,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: that would be... This is D-1-103-OVP, Your Honor, for the first AOM issued on September 14, 2023.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's the counterpart of P-1-12-A.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And isunod ko na po yung pangalawang AOM na na-issue on October 3, 2023. This is D-1-104-OVP for the defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Which is P-1-12-B for the prosecution.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, Mr. Witness, napansin ko na yung date is September 14, 2023, nang unan yung AOM. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po. And that was actually...
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Just a few days after the budget hearing of COA held August 24, 2023, kung saan may mga legislators that, well, asked COA to look into the OVP confidential funds. Are you aware of that? Just if you're aware.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: I am not aware of that.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That's okay. Now, I'll just move on to the AOMs themselves.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Kahapon, nasasabi niyo po na nagkakaproblema tayo sa may nakita kayong finding doon sa physical and financial plan. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At yan po ay nakasaad din sa inyong findings dyan. Tama po ba? You referred to, if I'm not mistaken, and please correct me if I'm wrong, item 4.2 of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Maari nyo po bang basahin yung 4.2 ng Joint Circular para lang po sa kalaman natin lahat?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under 4.2 of the Joint Circular, all allocations of CEF and or IF shall be supported with physical and financial plan indicating the proposed amount allocated for each program, project, and activity where disbursements pertaining to the CE and IA shall be based.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you po, Mr. Witness. Dito po sa kanilang physical and financial plan, the program stated is actually the good government program. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung binabasa ko lang.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the document. Based
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: on the document.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At ang expected outcome ay safe implementation of OVP initiatives and confidence building. Based on the document.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the document.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: At
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ang physical target will be number of areas with surveillance. and confidential activities conducted or monitored.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: As well as the number of activities. Tama po ba? At ayon po dun sa binasa n'yo, wala naman pong guidelines on how specific it would be. Correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Well, nakalagay po kasi dito, dapat i-indicate yung each program, activity, and project na pagbabasayan ng disbursement ng CF. Apo. I
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: won't argue with you. So, basically, Yung finding n'yo po is based on your assessment as an auditor.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Well, since it is a plan, dapat po nakaindigay talaga dito kung paano nila gagastusin yung kanilang confidential fund.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That's okay. Yes, I'll accept that answer.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, nabanggit n'yo rin po na hindi po nagsubmit ng DEPs or Document Evidencing Payment. Tama po?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At yun po ay inilagay n'yo sa inyong AOM. Tama po?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: At nabanggit n'yo rin po na Sumagot ang OVP dito sa AOM na to. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po. At pagdating po doon sa sunod na step, which is the notice of suspension, tama po ba?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Would you agree with me na hindi na po na-carry over yung issue doon sa physical and financial plan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes. So, ibig sabihin, tinanggap nyo po yung explanation.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Well, ang purpose po kasi namin kung bakit namin nirequire yung specific confidential activities dun sa PF is para makita kung paano gagastusin. noong OBP, yung kanilang confidential fund. Pero since nilagay naman na po nila doon sa kanilang reverse accomplishment report yung specific confidential activities and even submitted documentary evidence of payment, so hindi na po namin hinanap ulit yung physical and financial plan. Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Salamat po. Thank you for that answer. Ngayon po, kasi kanina, sinasabi, well kahapon actually, not kanina, sinasabi nyo walang sinabmit. Ang ibig nyo lang pong sabihin sa walang sinabmit is at the time. na bago kayong mag-issue ng AOM. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Walang sinubmit na DEP.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, kasi sinamit po nila yung DEPs after we issued both AOFs po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Apo,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: thank you po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ngayon, punta naman po tayo doon sa Notice of Suspension. Nandun pa po kayo eh, di ba, noong Notice of Suspension?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And you suspended in audit the amount of 125 million. We are showing him a copy of the Notice of Suspension, Your Honor. This is Exhibit D-1-107-OVP for the reference of the Honorable Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: NP-1-13-A, on the part of the prosecution. Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So, dito po, as you mentioned earlier, you were satisfied with already the submission of the accomplishment report ng OVP, that's why nawala na po yung issue sa physical and financial.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po ako satisfied dahil compliant yung accomplishment report nila, kundi dahil nilagay lang nila yung specific confidential activities na pinaggamitan nung kanilang pondo.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So, nawala na po yung sa PFP na findings sa AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the NS po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Based on the NS. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Thank you. Ngayon, pagdating dito sa notice of suspension, I just wanted to focus on doon sa documentary evidencing success pagdating sa rewards.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Nabanggit nyo po, this is 4.8.5 paragraph B specifically of the Joint Circular, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And yun din po yung nakasaad dito sa Notice of Suspension na reference, meaning the provision of the JC specified. At nabanggit nyo rin po kahapon na wala pong guidelines specifically under 4.8.5 that shows how specific you should be in terms of the documents evidencing success. Wala
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po akong na-mention na walang specific guidelines po. Ang sabi ko lang, hindi sinabi ko anong specific document yung hinihingi. Wala, may sinabi
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: ko po kayong walang prescribed format, basically.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please misleading the witness to my recollection, did not say that. He said that in accordance with 4.8.5, these are the requirements, A, B, and C, and the submissions of the Vice President and the DepEd are not compliant, Your Honor. With
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the indulgence of councils for the parties, Mr. Wamil, base po sa guidelines, hindi tulad nung ibang mga format na sinasubmit na may pro forma na nasa annex noong 2015-1, wala pong pro forma na pag-liquidate na dokumento, sangayon sa 4.8.5. Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: based on this provision.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: May ibang provision bang nagre-require ng specific na paraan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala na po, Your
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Honor. Ito lang po. 4.8.5.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Witness. You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, pagdating po sa OVP, alam nyo po ba kung sumagot sila sa notice of suspension na ito within the prescribed period given under the notice of suspension?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Wala na po ako sa ICO nung submit sila ng
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: suspension. Okay po. So I will no longer ask you about that. Probably for another witness na lang po. Punta na lang po tayo sa
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: OVP Confidential Funds for 2023.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: You confirm, Mr. Witness, na ang OVP Confidential Funds for 2023 ay nakapag-issue rin kayo ng AOMs for the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd quarter. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: For the 1st and 2nd lang po kasi yung 3rd quarter, nag-drop po ako and hindi ko na po naabutan yung issuance noon dahil nag-transfer out na po ako sa EFAP.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. At
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: hindi nyo rin po alam kung
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Just if you're aware, kung sumagot ang OVP doon sa mga AOMs n'yo, hindi nyo rin po alam yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Sige. Diretso na lang po tayo sa DepEd para
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: hindi na po tayo tumagal. Sa DepEd po, nakapag-issue rin po kayo ng AOMs, tama? At least for the first and second quarter nandun pa po kayo.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po. And kanina po, pinag-uusapan po natin yung mga disbursement vouchers ng DepEd. Kung saan, natukoy n'yo doon na hindi compliant dahil MOOE yung nakasulat sa disbursement vouchers. Tama po ba? Naalala n'yo po yun?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Um, sinagot ko lang po yung tanong ni Atty. Lorna kanina. At
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: ang tanong n'yo, ang sagot n'yo po, natatandaan n'yo po ba yung sagot n'yo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ay MOOE siya at hindi confidential funds. Yes po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, Mr. Witness, I will show you a page of the General Appropriations Act.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: And for reference, Your Honors, this is Exhibit D-1-14-DE, Your Honors. And D-1-42-DE for the defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may approach the witness as well as counsel for the panel of prosecutors.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So, dito po sa page 376, volume 118, number 52, General Provisions Act FY 2023, klarong-klaro po na ang confidential intelligence and extraordinary expenses is under maintenance and other operating expenses, which is the MOOE. Pero if I may clarify lang po kasi, yung
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: MOOE kasi is very broad. So hindi lang confidential fund yung covered niya.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Apo, we will get to that, Your Honor.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: DV,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: sa
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: nakasulat.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Kaya po dito, sa ating naging disbursement voucher,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: With permission of Atty. Powa, yes.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Observations and
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Manifestations, Counsel.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, this document violates the original document rule. First, it is a photocopy. It is not even a photocopy of anything that is certified, Your Honor. Although, under the original document rule, you can dispense with the presentation of the original. If you present the original first and then substitute a copy, because a copy, a photocopy, is now considered likewise if properly authenticated as an original. This is a scrap of paper, Your Honor. We don't even know general appropriations of who, of which administration.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: consisting of how many pages, Your Honor?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This particular document, Your Honor, should not even be testified to because we don't know its provenance. For all we know, we don't know where this document came from.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: We
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: object, therefore, to this document, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the comment of Atty. Poa?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honors, the copy we are showing is actually a certified true copy of the Commission on Audit, certified by Davin E. Bakay, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Certified through copy of the part of the GA?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Yes,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Anyway, counsel, we will be ruling on the admissibility of these documents when the formal offer is made after the presentation of evidence in chief by the respondents.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We submit, Your Honor, but as another observation, Your Honor, we are aware, I think counsel is aware, that if you produce and you ask questions on a portion of a document, then you are compelled to produce the whole document, Your Honor. We want this on file. Produce the whole ga'a. For all we know, Your Honor, there may be provisions in that ga'a which contradicts the provision he's saying. So he is compelled under the rules, Your Honor. In addition to the rules of admissibility, he is compelled to produce the whole ga'a. And we want that on record, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: presiding officer has already ruled. The manifestation and objection of the council is duly noted. Council may proceed. Thank you, Your Honor. And
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: under the disbursement voucher, exhibit D-1-58-DE, nakasulat po na MOOE, replenishment of cash advance under maintenance and other operating expenses authorized under page 376 of RA Number 11936, which is precisely the page of the GAA.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pero marami po kasing nakalagay na expense items under MOUE in this page po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: We
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: will accept that answer, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Now, Mr. Witness, pagdating po sa DepEd
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Confidential Funds, as you mentioned, you issued the first two AOMs.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Tama po. I mean, AOM for the first and second quarter.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Pero hindi nyo na po natanggap yung response?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kasi wala
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: na kayo sa IGFAO?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: But would you know, just curious, would you know kung ano yung present status nitong mga AOMs na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po. I don't have personal knowledge about that.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. So you wouldn't know of whether may credit notice o wala?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, sir.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: But since you're an auditor, ano po ang ibig sabihin ng credit notice para sa isang
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: auditor? Kapag sinabing credit notice, yung document submitted ay already passed in audit na
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Opo, passed in audit, meaning allowed?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, but subject
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: to the reopening of the audit later
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: on po. Okay, thank you Mr. Witness. Ngayon Mr. Witness, since hanggang dun lang naman yung naging saklaw talaga ng inyong service, I don't want to prolong this any longer. Gusto ko lang makita, based on your findings, AOM, di ba? Tapos yung notice of suspension para sa OVP and AOMs for DepEd. These are preliminary findings, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, kasi nirequire pa naman sa agency na mag-justify yung findings and submit the documents being sought po dun sa... Opo,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: at based po dito sa findings n'yo, wala namang pong expressly nakasulat na may misappropriation at this point.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Actually, yung presumption of misuse kasi nasa item 8.3 na kapag hindi nag-liquidate or failure of liquidation of the accountable officers upon due demand shall be a prima facie evidence that such fund has been put to personal benefit or misuse.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: But I am just asking for the response na... Meron po bang expressly nakasulat sa mga findings niya?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ask and answered, Your Honor. That is a presumption po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: May expressly po ba na nakasulat na may niisang kusing na napunta sa bulsa ng Vice Presidente?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ask and answered, Your Honor. Wait, don't answer. That
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, has been asked and answered. Sustained, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor. Sustained, Counsel. I think what you're getting at. Modify. Modify your question. You can get it.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. So, basically po, ang findings n'yo ay preliminary lamang. Wala pong any conclusive finding pa as to any misappropriation. Yun lang po ang tanong ko.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang sabi kasi sa circular, upon failure to liquidate, meron kang presumption.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ask
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: and answer, Your Honor. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness is not responsive. Kindly respond. I think the question is quite simple, Mr. Romil.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Preliminary pa lang. So wala pang any conclusive finding as to any misappropriation. Yun na lang po. Para lang po masagot nyo na ng diretso.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi naman po kasi kailangan i-state doon sa findings. Again, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor, non-responsive. Let the Presiding Officer be the one to do it or try to do it.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kapag ka nag-issue po kayo ng AOM, Audit Observation Memorandum, failure to liquidate na po ba yun? O may mga observation pa lang kayo? Kailan masasabing may failure to liquidate na no? Pag may notice of disallowance na, notice of suspension, o AOM pa lang?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nakalagay po kasi sa Joint Circular, Your Honor, under 8.3, failure to liquidate by the accountable officer upon due demand shall be a prima facie evidence. Opo, again, Mr. Wamila,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: yung pag-issue nyo po ba ng AOM? Pasok na sa failure to liquidate upon due demand o hindi pa po?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi pa po sa AOM, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kasi wala pong due demand sa AOM?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: At may sasabi mo rin bang wala pang failure to liquidate o meron na?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pag sa AOM po wala, pero pag sa NS po, since meron ng first issuance which is considered as demand, so meron na po sa NS. So AOM
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: wala pa, pag NS, meron
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ng demand? At meron ng failure to liquidate. Opo, since sa AOM po, nirequire na silang i-justify and i-submit yung mga documents na hindi nila na-submit.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pero sa AOM, wala pa kang ganun.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Okay. Counsel, your witness. Thank you. And lastly, gusto ko lang ito ma-clarify. Of course, the witness was a state auditor of the ICFAO. So, rekomendatory lang po ang function ninyo. Hindi po kayo nag-de-decide. Pagdating sa, lalong-lalo na, pagdating sa notice of this allowance. Tama po ba?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po. It's the function of the commission proper.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Wamil, Atty. Wamil. I thank you for your patience.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That is all for this witness, Your Honor. Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, counsel, respondent, redirect, if any, counsel, for the panel of prosecutors.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yes, Your Honor, with your permission.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proceed
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: with
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: her
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: redirect. Mr. Witness.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Tinalong sa iyo ng counsel for the respondent kung meron kang special training para mag-audit ng confidential funds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Kailangan ba ng special training para mag-audit ng confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: No, ma'am. Hindi? Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ang basihan mo, sinabi mo, when you answered is, ang
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: basihan mo ay itong joint circular.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Now,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: tinalong sa iyo ng counsel, Kung alam mo na ang office of the President ang siyang nagbigay ng grant,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: tama?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At ang sagot mo? Oo.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You answered on cross on the question of counsel for the respondent if you are aware that the grant was given to the Vice President by the President.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po. And
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you answered yes.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pag binigay ba ng presidente, like in this instance, ang confidential funds, wala nang obligasyon mag-liquidate ang vice president ng paggamit niya sa confidential funds na yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Meron po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Meron po siyang
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: obligation to liquidate.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Obligasyon. Pag-grant ba ng Office of the President? Eh, exempted na ang Vice President na mag-submit ng mga dokumento. Your Honor,
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Council for Respondent? That is leading.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Redirect, Your Honor, this, Council opened the door.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Not covered
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: by cross, even, Your Honor. Your
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Honor, Council opened the door. Council opened the door to this line of questioning because he said, a grant was given by the President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Objection,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection is overruled. Witness may answer if he knows. Kung alam mo, Mr. Wamil, Pakisagot po yung tanong ni Atty. Kapunan. Can you repeat the question, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang grant ba ng confidential funds ng isang presidente to a vice president, this president in particular, to the vice president, does it exempt the vice president for accounting, for the use of that confidential funds under your joint circular?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: No po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So kailangan pa rin, sinasabi mo, na compliant? Mag-comply.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: lang ang Office of the President. Kung binigyan rin ng grant ang Department Secretary of Education, kailangan rin.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit? Ano ba ang nature ng pondo na yan? Pera ba yan ng Presidente?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Since ang confidential fund po ay public fund, so kailangan po ma-properly account. So kailangan nilang i-liquidate properly and completely yung kanilang cash advances from the confidential fund.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So ang sinasabi mo? at nasa rationalityo ng Joint Circular. Section 1, public funds, public accountability, public officer. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Opo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Walang exemption. Hindi exemption, si Sara Duterte para mag-account.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sinabi rin, counsel
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: for the Vice President also said, counsel for, yeah, the Vice President also said, Tinanong ka tungkol sa ano ba yung accrual method of accounting? Pakiulit, ano yung accrual method?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Under the accrual method po, the expenses is recorded upon incoherence and not upon payment po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Allowed ba ito, itong accrual method of accounting, sa pag-evaluate ng confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: No, ma'am, kasi kailangan po talagang binayaran yung expenses po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So, hindi pwedeng accrual, parang lista. Hindi
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po pwedeng lista.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi pwedeng lista-lista. Kung binayaran, dapat cash out.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At kung cash out, dapat may resibo.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: So,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: hindi pwede ang accrual. Mr. Witness, tinanong rin sa'yo,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: itong utilization
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: of confidential funds. Nakalagay utilization of confidential funds. Tinanong sa iyo ng counsel, hindi ba dapat confidential rin? Do not divulge information on the use of confidential funds. Tama ba ang interpretation ng counsel for the respondent?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, that was not my interpretation. I was merely asking based on the... the quote was circular that he read, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Just that. Just on that matter. Noted. Witness may answer.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ang tanong, sabi ng counsel, e confidential funds yan, bawal ang mag-reveal ng confidential information, citing certain provision and revised penal code, certain guidelines, which you haven't seen, pag confidential funds ba? lahat ng information na hinihingi sa inyo, kagaya ng sangginastos, yung milyon-milyon na yan sa medicine, ay, bawal yan. Confidential yan. Pwede ba yan, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po. Since ang confidential fund po ay public fund, so dapat po ay properly accounted po ito. And since ang involved po ay confidential fund, so it must follow the strict accounting and auditing guidance po to prevent misuse.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Confidential ba yung, uy? Bawal mo sabihin, sang grocery binili.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: As
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: an answered, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: As
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: an answered.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: This is
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: food, Your Honor. And all the items there. Lahat ng items na sinabi natin. Food, medicine, transport. As an answered, Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor, I ask for a ruling.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, I only ask for the medicine. I'm itemizing. As an
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: answered previously, Counsel. Counsel for Responder is correct. Currently move on to the next point.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, sinabi sa'yo.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: na dapat, since this is accountable, strict, sinabi mo na ang pagka-interpret ng joint circular na yan, eh, nandito sa, dapat strict, no?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Because public funds ito. Pag sinabi bang strict interpretation, and I will quote,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: strict accounting,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: The utilization of such funds is generally confidential and classified by nature, which requires not only strong internal controls.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nakita
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: ba natin sa mga dokumento na sinubmit ng Vice President at ng Secretary of DepEd, nakita ba natin yung mga internal controls?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Bakit?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, the witness is incompetent to answer because he only based his audit on the documents provided. He has no knowledge on the internal controls of the Department of Education or the Office of the Vice President, Your Honor. If
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: knows based on his observation of the documents submitted to him, only in so far as that is concerned, Mr. Wamel, give me an answer.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents, may mga... Deficiencies pa rin po na-noted. So, it can be inferred na hindi strong yung kanilang internal control.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Ano mga deficiencies na na-notice mo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yung kanilang mga documents, some of the documents ay hindi compliant dun sa requirements ng Joint Circular 2015-01.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Acknowledgement receipts na walang dates?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po. Walang date. Yung iba naka-date ng 2023 even if the period covered ay 2022.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Liquidating documents para sa... Submitted 2023 para sa period 2022. May internal control ba yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Actually, nasubmit naman po nila on time yung kanilang liquidation.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Mga acknowledgement receipts na walang signatures?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Internal control ba yan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: That should have been prevented by a strong internal control.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nakalagay rin dito in this section.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Strict auditing rules to prevent mishandling and... improper application of the funds. So, sinabi mo na dapat strict ang compliance. Ikaw pa, as a state auditor, meron ka bang diskresyon sa pag-apply ng rules na to?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Can you repeat the question, po? Okay.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You said that the basis for your evaluation are the express provisions of these rules.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Do you exercise any discretion?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: We exercise professional judgments. Kailangan po namin i-evaluate if yung documents ay compliant sa requirements.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Professional judgment.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: But is this judgment based on personal opinion?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Is this judgment based on, ayoko yung mukha ni tong officer na to, bias? Is it based on bias?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: What is it based on? Your professional judgment is based on what?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Professional judgment is based on the experience and the applicable laws, rules, and regulations.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. Counsel also mentioned 3.9, which is confidential expenses.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I don't think I mentioned that, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Then I will mention it.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Not subject of the cross,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Are you referring to the JMC, Counsel?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: accounting, this council asked on how confidential expenses or funds are being accounted for. This is germane to the questions on cross.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No, my question, counsel, is what 3.9 are you referring to? 3.9 of what?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 3.9 of the Joint Circular, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Is there one?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: It's confidential expenses, which is, it refers to those expenses pertaining related to surveillance activities, etc., Your Honor. Your
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Honor, beyond the scope of the cross, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please. He opened the door. He says, confidential funds. He says, confidential funds, do not disclose information.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, please, we have to put a limit to at least, you know, apply what is in the rules of court suppletorily, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Subject to the discretion of the court, the redirect and cover matters, not... Covered by the cross. The same is true with your accrued cross, counsel, later on. We submit, Your Honor. Counsel may proceed with her question. Witness may answer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Okay. In confidential expenses 3.9, nakalagay dito, in your evaluation of confidential, or liquidation of confidential funds or confidential expenses, nakalagay dito, are intended to support the mandate or operations of the agency, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Nasa mandato ba ng office ng vice president ang magkaroon ng confidential funds?
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Calls for an opinion, Your Honor, that the witness is not qualified to answer.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: It's confidential, Your Honor. He knows what are allowed, what are not allowed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection sustained. Witness is not competent to answer whether or not it is part of the OVP's function, much less a DepEd, to have confidential funds. That he did not see any confidential funds when he was with Kowa Ikfaw does not mean that it is allowed or not allowed. Kindly move on to your next point, counsel, please.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: You also mentioned that you
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: were asked about 4.2. Correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: I
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: confirm that.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And in 4.2, it says there, shall be supported with physical and financial plan. Indicating the proposed amount allocated for each program, activity, and project.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito ba at ang sinabi ng counsel eh, pinakita naman sa'yo yung dokumento. Bakit hindi mo siya, bakit? Why are you saying that there is no indication of what these projects are? What the disbursements pertain to? And what the confidential expense is based on? Why did you say that there is no?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Dahil hindi po naka-indicate dun sa kanilang physical and financial plan yung specific confidential activities.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi pa pwede ang substantial compliance dyan?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kasi ang requirement mo ng Joint Circular ay strict compliance.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Strict, hindi substantial.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Now, in
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: 4.8.5,
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: counsel
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: makes mention in his cross that sa office of the Vice President, ang SDO, Senior Dispersing Officer, Special, SDO, IC Acosta, tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Sa OBPS, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At sa DepEd ay ang SDO ay si Fajarda. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At tama daw sabi ng counsel na tama lang talaga na sila yung payees.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Implying na silang tumanggap.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Implying na, ito ba, pag silang tumanggap, sila lang nakakaalam?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Hindi.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Kasi based on
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: the
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Joint Circular, si head of the agency po yung may responsibility to oversee the agency-wide use of the confidential fund and to ensure compliance with the requirements of the Joint Circular.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sino ang boss?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sino ang head of agency ng Office of the Vice President?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Si Vice President Sara Duterte po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: At nakalagay dito sa Sinayat na Provision 4.8.5, nakalagay, as among the requirements, approval by the head of agency. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Ito. At nakita naman natin sa mga documents na pinisend natin, eh lahat may approval ng head of agency si Sara Duterte. Tama?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Yung accomplishment report.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes,
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Sa accomplishment report. Hindi lang sa OVP, sa DepEd. Meron nakalagay. Approved, attested, certified, correct. Sino ang nag-certify?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Even yung certification po nung accountable officer on the utilization of the confidential plans of both the OBP and DepEd ay attested po ni Vice President.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: So even if counsel says the SDO is Acosta for the OBP and the SDO for the DepEd is Fajarda, still the head of the agency, who in all the documents we have seen, signed, attested, approved, certified, is Sara Duterte as Vice President and as Secretary of the DepEd, correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on the documents, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: On 8.3, tinanong sa'yo, conclusive ba? 8.3, you mentioned prima facie findings. Tinanong sa'yo, is this conclusive?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Hindi po. Ito'y prima facie po.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Pero miski na prima facie findings. Meron bang presumption? Is there a presumption of innocence here? Is there a presumption of guilt? As a matter of fact, expressly says, there is a presumption of misuse and that it is used for personal benefit. Tama?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Based on this provision po, yes ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: And so far, unless proven otherwise, that presumption still holds.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: is presumed to have misused or to have used it for personal benefit, Mr. Witness. Correct?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Based on 8.3. Correct?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: No further questions, Your Honor. Mayroon pa daw.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, recross.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Recross just two points, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Just
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: two quick points. Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: respondent, may proceed.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Unang-unal sa lahat po, ukol po doon sa acknowledgement receipts. Pagdating po sa mga undated na nabanggit nyo naman at nasa report nyo naman, you would confirm na sumugot ang OVP pero hindi nyo niya inabutan ang sagot or meaning hindi nyo na alam kung sumugot man ang OVP dun sa notice of suspension?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, hindi ko naman nabutan.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So probably for another witness. Ngayon dun sa unang sinabi po ng kagalang-galang ng si Atty. Capunan sa pagiging exempt, niminsan ba humingi ang exemption? ang vice-presidente sa audit ng kanyang confidential funds?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Ang humingi po ng, actually, meron nag-request po na kung pwedeng audit query na lang yung i-issue instead of AOM. So parang exception po yun dun sa provision ng Joint Circular na AOM yung i-issue.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Ang exemption po yung tinatanong ko. Just an exemption on the audit itself. The conduct of the audit, meaning nagsubmit po ba sila ng liquidation reports?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, po.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: nag-responde po ba sila sa AOM n'yo?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes po, pero hindi pa rin po
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: sila compliant sa requirements.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: No, Your Honor, I'm not asking that. I'm just asking for, nag-submit ba sila? Did they respond to your AOMs?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Nag-submit pero hindi po full yung submission.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: So they did not ignore your AOMs?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Pero hindi pa rin
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: po full
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: submission yung ginawa nila.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question, Mr. Wamilis, did they submit a response? Whatever your evaluation of the response, complete or incomplete, is another matter.
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, they submitted a response po dun sa AOM. So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: they submitted a response.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: That is all for recourse, Your Honor. Again, Mr. Witness, thank you for your patience. With the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: permission of our colleagues, it's 2.30 and session was called by the Senate President to be convened at 3 p.m. May we continue with our interjections for this witness tomorrow.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And I have listed already those who would like to make interjections.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: In this order, Senator Tulfo, Rafi, Senator Bamacino, Senator Pangilinan, Senator Erwin Tulfo, Senate President, Senator Jewel Villanueva, Senator Judge Riza Ontiveros, Senator Judge Padilla, and Senator Judge Aimee Marcos, and Senator Judge Ejercito. In that order. It'll be in the journal anyway tomorrow.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Your Honor, please, before any other announcements, can we ask that the witness be excused?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, the chair was about to do that. Mr. Walmel, you're excused for the day. Kindly be back again tomorrow without need or necessity of issuing another subpoena. Can we rely on your word that you will be attending tomorrow's hearing for the continuation and hopefully closure of your testimony before the impeachment court?
Atty. Roderick C. Wamil: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Asahan po namin. You are excused, sir. Thank you po sa inyong kooperasyon at oras at pasensya.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before we adjourn, the Chair notes that the next witness, Ms. Cylene May L. Del Campo, was only subpoenaed to appear before the court on August 3 and August 4. The clerk is thereby directed to issue, and the Sergeant-at-Arms to serve, a subpoena for the appearance of Ms. Cylene May L. Del Campo of the COA-ICFAO, which subpoena shall remain valid from August 5, 2026 until August 11, 2026. With respect to Marevic Pareja, who was subpoenaed for August 4 and 5, the issuance of subpoena will depend on the Chair's ruling on the motion for judicial notice of the prosecution which the Chair will rule upon after hearing the respondent. Orally or through a written manifestation or motion regarding this matter tomorrow before we adjourn. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: panel of prosecutors, with the permission of the lead prosecutor, allow the presiding officer to finish with one other administrative matter. The panel of prosecutors also filed a motion to set a conference for the transfer of exhibit markings.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to be set at 4 p.m. on Wednesday, tomorrow, August 5, 2026 for the transfer of markings from copies previously marked during the pre-trial order. Given that this is administrative in nature, the request and the motion is granted. The counsel-respondent is directed as well as counsel for the panel of prosecutors to assign lawyers for this change of markings. to be conducted again for the record at 4 p.m. of Wednesday, August 5, 2026. That is tomorrow.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes. May
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: I be recognized, Your Honor? Good afternoon.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before the lead counsel for the respondent, I think the lead prosecutor earlier asked for recognition. What is the pressure of the Honorable Luistro?
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: First of all, Your Honor, we just want to acknowledge your just... Your pronouncement earlier about the setting of the transfer of marking of exhibits that will be on August 5, 4 p.m. This pertains particularly to exhibit P4-3 and series through P4-35B. Second, Your Honor, we also acknowledge the pronouncement of the impeachment court relative to the oral or written comment of the defense to the earlier motion of the prosecution that was filed on August 3. That is to take judicial notice of the hearings conducted both by the House Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability and the Committee on Justice, Your Honor. That's for the record. And third, Your Honor, this is in line also with Another pronouncement of the impeachment court in compliance with, relative to our compliance to the five-day notice rule. We will be submitting the list of witnesses for next week as well as the request for issuance of subpoena tomorrow, August 5, because the same will depend on... On the conclusion of the testimony of Ms. Cylene del Campo as well as the ruling of the impeachment court with regards to the motion to take judicial notice on the hearing of the two committees of the House of Representatives, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's all?
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Julie noted. What is the pleasure of the lead counsel of the respondent?
Sheila C. Sison: Thank you, Your Honor. First, with respect to the motion to set confidence for the transfer of civic markings, I just note that under paragraph 3 on page 2 of this motion, the prosecution is also requesting for the portion of Arturo Lascagna's affidavit, paragraphs 270, 270 paragraph B, and 270 paragraph D. to be also marked. Now, I would just like to put on record that we're objecting even to the marking of this particular exhibit consistent with the ruling of this court when we objected to the reading session of the NBI Director Melvin Matibag when he testified and was cross-examined by Defense Counsel Attorney Mark Bin Luan. So we object to the marking of This portion of Arturo Lascagna's affidavit. As of this point, no witness has yet testified on this affidavit and it is on record, if we review the record of the court, that that supposed affidavit was unnotarized and was not signed by anybody, let alone identified by any competent witness. And also, Your Honor, the motion is to set conference for the transfer of exhibit markings. Now, this presupposes that there has already been a marking on the original document. Now, if there is no competent witness who has identified the affidavit of Las Cañas, then there is no reason for a supposed transfer of exhibit markings. We object. We object to item number three of this motion. We will not agree. If the presiding officer will rule to allow even the pre-marking or the marking of this item under this motion, then we would like to have our continuing objection to the allowance of even the marking of this particular exhibit put on record, Your Honor. Thank you.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: May we respond, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: To afford the court some time to rule on the matter, let the marking and premarkings proceed tomorrow without prejudice to the ruling of the chair with finality in open court with respect to the objection raised by the lead counsel for the prosecutor at the appropriate time. Most likely tomorrow also. No, probably on Monday, counsel, before we finally act on it after the marking and premarking to be done. tomorrow. Again, that is without prejudice to noting the continuing objection of the counsel for the respondent on the matter. In any way, we will be finally ruling on the admissibility of these documentary pieces of evidence once formal offer is made.
Sheila C. Sison: We will do that, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, counsel. If there are no other matters to be taken up, again, with the permission of my colleagues, fellow senator-judges, let their interjections be done.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tomorrow, when we resume at 10pm, we will be convening at 3.30pm for the advice of our Senate President this afternoon. Trial is adjourned until tomorrow, August 5, at 10am in the morning.